<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><chapter id="c0015" version="5.3" docsubtype="chp" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.elsevier.com/xml/bk/dtd" xmlns:ce="http://www.elsevier.com/xml/common/dtd" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><info><ce:pii>B978-0-7234-3864-9.00003-4</ce:pii><ce:doi>10.1016/B978-0-7234-3864-9.00003-4</ce:doi><ce:isbn>978-0-7234-3864-9</ce:isbn><ce:copyright type="full-transfer" year="2015">Elsevier Ltd</ce:copyright></info><ce:label>3</ce:label><ce:title>The clerking</ce:title><objectives><ce:section-title id="st0010">Objectives</ce:section-title><ce:para id="p0010">The key learning points for this chapter:<ce:list id="l0010"><ce:list-item id="u0010"><ce:label>•</ce:label><ce:para id="p0015">Structure your clerking in a logical manner.</ce:para></ce:list-item><ce:list-item id="u0015"><ce:label>•</ce:label><ce:para id="p0020">Appreciate factors in the clerking that make it easier for colleagues to review.</ce:para></ce:list-item><ce:list-item id="u0020"><ce:label>•</ce:label><ce:para id="p0025">Vary the clerking according to the patient's symptoms.</ce:para></ce:list-item><ce:list-item id="u0025"><ce:label>•</ce:label><ce:para id="p0030">Know how to conclude the clerking and the purpose that this serves.</ce:para></ce:list-item></ce:list></ce:para></objectives><ce:sections><ce:section id="s0010"><ce:section-title id="st0015">INTRODUCTION</ce:section-title><ce:para id="p0035">The doctor's ‘clerking’ is a written summary of the patient's history and examination. It is a legal document and should be precise, complete and legible. Avoid using abbreviations – although the meaning may be obvious to you, they may be interpreted very differently in a different speciality or hospital. However, in real life, abbreviations litter the medical notes and you ought to be familiar with the most common ones.</ce:para><ce:para id="p0040">The ‘history of presenting complaint’ section is a useful place to document the most relevant positive and negative historical points. Less relevant details can be recorded in their appropriate subsection. For example, in the case presented here, the relevant negative historical points have been included in the ‘history of presenting complaint’ rather than elsewhere in the clerking.</ce:para><ce:para id="p0045">At the end of the clerking, the salient points should be emphasized in a summary statement. You should then, always, compile a ‘problem list’. This is often forgotten by students and junior doctors alike, but is invaluable in planning appropriate investigations and management. In some patients, it will not be appropriate, or even possible, to take a full history and perform a full clinical examination (e.g. in an emergency situation). We have outlined a clinical example.</ce:para><ce:para id="p0050">As a student, it is good practice to be very thorough as it helps you to learn the relevant questions and to avoid missing anything important. However, with practice, you will learn to tailor carefully the clinical approach to each patient based on their individual, and often very different, needs.</ce:para></ce:section><ce:section id="s0015"><ce:section-title id="st0020">MEDICAL SAMPLE CLERKING</ce:section-title><ce:para id="p0055"><ce:display><ce:figure id="f0025"><ce:link locator="u03-01a-9780723436331" id="lk0010"/><ce:link locator="u03-01b-9780723436331" id="lk0015"/><ce:link locator="u03-01c-9780723436331" id="lk0020"/></ce:figure></ce:display></ce:para></ce:section></ce:sections></chapter>