<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter id="c0060" version="5.2" docsubtype="chp" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.elsevier.com/xml/bk/dtd"
         xmlns:ce="http://www.elsevier.com/xml/common/dtd" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <info>
        <ce:pii>B978-0-7234-3863-2.00012-X</ce:pii>
        <ce:doi>10.1016/B978-0-7234-3863-2.00012-X</ce:doi>
        <ce:isbn>978-0-7234-3863-2</ce:isbn>
        <ce:copyright type="full-transfer" year="2015">Elsevier Ltd</ce:copyright>
    </info>
    <ce:floats>
        <ce:figure id="f0010">
            <ce:label>Fig. 12.1</ce:label>
            <ce:caption>
                <ce:simple-para id="sp0010">Dissociative (‘conversion’) disorders</ce:simple-para>
            </ce:caption>
            <ce:link locator="f12-01-9780723436362" id="lk0010"/>
        </ce:figure>
        <ce:figure id="f0015">
            <ce:label>Fig. 12.2</ce:label>
            <ce:caption>
                <ce:simple-para id="sp0015" role="caption">Parkes's stages of normal bereavement</ce:simple-para>
            </ce:caption>
            <ce:link locator="f12-02-9780723436362" id="lk0015"/>
        </ce:figure>
        <ce:figure id="f0020">
            <ce:label>Fig. 12.3</ce:label>
            <ce:caption>
                <ce:simple-para id="sp0020">Differential diagnosis for patients presenting with a reaction to stress or
                    trauma
                </ce:simple-para>
            </ce:caption>
            <ce:link locator="f12-03-9780723436362" id="lk0020"/>
        </ce:figure>
    </ce:floats>
    <ce:label>12</ce:label>
    <ce:title>The patient with a reaction to a stressful event or bereavement</ce:title>
    <objectives>
        <ce:section-title id="st0010">Objectives</ce:section-title>
        <ce:para id="p0025">After this chapter you should have an understanding of:
            <ce:list id="l0025">
                <ce:list-item id="u0025">
                    <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                    <ce:para id="p0030">The definition of a stressful event</ce:para>
                </ce:list-item>
                <ce:list-item id="u0030">
                    <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                    <ce:para id="p0035">The different psychiatric disorders that can be induced by stressful or adverse
                        events
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:list-item>
                <ce:list-item id="u0035">
                    <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                    <ce:para id="p0040">How to distinguish between stress-induced psychiatric disorders</ce:para>
                </ce:list-item>
                <ce:list-item id="u0040">
                    <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                    <ce:para id="p0045">How to distinguish stress-induced psychiatric disorders from other psychiatric
                        disorders
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:list-item>
            </ce:list>
        </ce:para>
    </objectives>
    <ce:sections>
        <ce:para id="p0050">
            <ce:display>
                <ce:textbox role="alt2" id="b0010">
                    <ce:textbox-head>
                        <ce:title>Case summary</ce:title>
                    </ce:textbox-head>
                    <ce:textbox-body>
                        <ce:sections>
                            <ce:para id="p0055">Mrs PT, a 28-year-old divorced woman, was referred to a psychiatrist.
                                She was well and working as a cleaner until 3 months ago when, on her way to work one
                                evening, two men cornered her at a secluded bus shelter. They pushed her to the ground
                                and raped her, threatening to ‘slit her throat’ if she screamed. The men ran off when
                                they heard someone approaching, leaving Mrs PT shaken but with only superficial cuts and
                                bruises. She felt low in mood for a few days after the assault, but attempted to carry
                                on with her job and forget what had happened. In the month that followed, Mrs PT avoided
                                all attempts by her family and friends to talk about the incident. She became socially
                                withdrawn, only leaving the house to go to work. After a month, she started having
                                nightmares about the incident and would wake up drenched in sweat. Her work colleagues
                                noticed that she had become ‘jumpy and quick-tempered’ and that sudden movements or
                                noises startled her. She had also started avoiding public transportation and refused to
                                watch television for fear that something might remind her of the rape. Mrs PT finally
                                sought medical help after her work supervisor found her lying on the floor, seemingly in
                                a trance, screaming ‘Leave me alone!’ repeatedly. She recounted to her psychiatrist how
                                she ‘re-lived’ the rape in her mind and thought she could hear the the men threatening
                                her, just like they did during the incident. The psychiatrist noticed that Mrs PT could
                                not recall certain important aspects of the assault.
                            </ce:para>
                            <ce:para id="p8050">
                                <ce:italic>(For a discussion of the case study see the end of the chapter)</ce:italic>
                            </ce:para>
                        </ce:sections>
                    </ce:textbox-body>
                </ce:textbox>
            </ce:display>
        </ce:para>
        <ce:para id="p0065">It is not unusual to have some psychological symptoms after a stressful event or
            bereavement. However, in some cases, these symptoms may be more severe than expected, and impact upon
            everyday functioning. It is important to be able to distinguish a normal reaction to a difficult life event
            from a specific constellation of symptoms that denote psychopathology requiring clinical attention.
        </ce:para>
        <ce:section id="s0010">
            <ce:section-title id="st0015">DEFINITIONS AND CLINICAL FEATURES</ce:section-title>
            <ce:para id="p0070">When assessing someone who may have had a pathological response to a stressful event, it
                is important to explore two variables: (1) the nature and severity of the life event; and (2) the nature
                and severity of the person's reaction to the life event.
            </ce:para>
            <ce:section id="s0015">
                <ce:section-title id="st0020">Nature and severity of the life event</ce:section-title>
                <ce:section id="s0020">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0025">Stress</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0075">‘Psychosocial stressor’ is the term used for any life event, condition or
                        circumstance that places a strain on a person's current coping skills. It is important to
                        remember that what constitutes a ‘stressor’ is subjective, and dependent on the specific
                        person's ability to adapt or respond to a specific life challenge. For example, one student may
                        breeze through an exam without experiencing any stress, while another may feel incredibly
                        strained because of a perceived (or actual) mismatch between their ability and the demands of
                        the situation. Also note that the same person's coping skills vary throughout their
                        developmental life: the death of a distant relative may be far more stressful for a middle-aged
                        man contemplating his own mortality than for an ‘invincible’ adolescent.
                        <ce:display>
                            <ce:textbox id="b0015" role="alt1">
                                <ce:textbox-head>
                                    <ce:title>COMMUNICATION</ce:title>
                                </ce:textbox-head>
                                <ce:textbox-body>
                                    <ce:sections>
                                        <ce:para id="p0080">Whenever a patient presents with low mood or anxiety, always
                                            check for possible psychosocial stressors and establish how (if at all) they
                                            relate to the onset of symptoms. If the stressor seemed insignificant,
                                            verify how it was perceived by the patient. Remember, a seemingly innocuous
                                            life event may be a significant psychosocial stressor for a vulnerable
                                            patient (e.g. a change of accommodation for an elderly widow).
                                        </ce:para>
                                    </ce:sections>
                                </ce:textbox-body>
                            </ce:textbox>
                        </ce:display>
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0025">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0030">Traumatic stress</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0085">A traumatic stressor occurs outside the range of normal human experience, and
                        its magnitude means that it would be experienced as traumatic by most people. This type of
                        stress occurs in situations where a person feels that their own (or a loved one's) physical or
                        psychological integrity is under serious threat. These include natural disasters, physical or
                        sexual assaults, serious road traffic accidents, terrorist attacks, torture and military combat.
                        Bereavement is a special case of traumatic stress that will be discussed later.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
            </ce:section>
            <ce:section id="s0030">
                <ce:section-title id="st0035">Nature and severity of patient's reaction</ce:section-title>
                <ce:para id="p0090">Some people seem to experience stressful or traumatic life events with minimal
                    symptoms, while others seem more susceptible to developing a diagnosable disorder. Depending on the
                    severity of the stressor and their underlying vulnerability, patients may develop: (1) an adjustment
                    disorder; (2) an acute stress reaction or post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD); (3) a dissociative
                    disorder; or (4) another major mental illness such as a depressive, anxiety or psychotic disorder.
                </ce:para>
                <ce:section id="s0035">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0040">Adjustment disorder</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0095">Feeling unable to cope is common at times of psychosocial stresses to which we
                        need to adapt or adjust (such as moving house, changing job or becoming a parent). However, when
                        symptoms are considered significant enough to be out of proportion to the original stressor, or
                        cause disturbance of social or occupational functioning, this can be described as an adjustment
                        disorder. For this diagnosis to be made, the emotional and/or behavioural symptoms need to occur
                        within 3 months (according to DSM-IV; ICD-10 states 1 month) of the original stressor. Although
                        it is assumed that the disorder would not have arisen without the original stressor, an
                        individual's personality and vulnerability to stress play an important contributing role.
                        Symptoms usually fully resolve within 6 months of onset, and if this is not the case,
                        consideration should be given to a different diagnosis.
                    </ce:para>
                    <ce:para id="p0100">Usually, adjustment disorder is characterized by mood and/or anxiety symptoms,
                        and this can occasionally be of severity sufficient to cause disturbances of conduct (e.g.
                        reckless driving, aggressive behaviour). Many people with adjustment disorder also experience
                        suicidal ideation.
                        <ce:display>
                            <ce:textbox role="alt0" id="b0020">
                                <ce:textbox-head>
                                    <ce:title>HINTS AND TIPS</ce:title>
                                </ce:textbox-head>
                                <ce:textbox-body>
                                    <ce:sections>
                                        <ce:para id="p0105">You should only diagnose an adjustment disorder when
                                            patients do not meet the criteria for a more specific diagnosis such as
                                            mood, psychotic or anxiety disorder (including PTSD), or a normal
                                            bereavement reaction.
                                        </ce:para>
                                    </ce:sections>
                                </ce:textbox-body>
                            </ce:textbox>
                        </ce:display>
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0040">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0045">Acute stress reaction</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0110">The symptoms of an acute stress reaction (combat fatigue, psychic shock) develop
                        immediately after, or within a few minutes of, a traumatic stressor. Typically, sufferers will
                        experience an initial ‘dazed’ state followed by possible disorientation and a narrowing of
                        attention with inability to process external stimuli. In some cases, this may be followed either
                        by a period of diminished responsiveness (to the extreme of a dissociative stupor) or
                        psychomotor agitation and overactivity. Patients may also have amnesia for the episode (see
                        <ce:cross-ref refid="f0010">Fig. 12.1</ce:cross-ref>
                        <ce:float-anchor refid="f0010"/>
                        for dissociative amnesia and stupor). These symptoms normally begin to diminish after 24–48
                        hours, and are usually minimal after 3 days.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0045">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0050">Post-traumatic stress disorder</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0115">The symptoms of post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) usually develop after 1
                        month but within 6 months of a traumatic stressor, and lead to significant distress or
                        functional impairment. Symptoms include all of the following:
                        <ce:list id="l0030">
                            <ce:list-item id="u0045">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0120">Repetitive re-experiencing of the traumatic event in the form of:
                                    <ce:list id="l9000">
                                        <ce:list-item id="u0050">
                                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                            <ce:para id="p0125">Flashbacks (intrusive, unwanted memories; vivid mental
                                                images or dreams of the original experience)
                                            </ce:para>
                                        </ce:list-item>
                                        <ce:list-item id="u0055">
                                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                            <ce:para id="p0130">Distress caused by internal or external cues that
                                                resemble the stressor (at times, patients may dissociate and experience
                                                the original event as though it were happening at that moment)
                                            </ce:para>
                                        </ce:list-item>
                                        <ce:list-item id="u0060">
                                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                            <ce:para id="p0135">Patients may also experience hallucinations and
                                                illusions.
                                            </ce:para>
                                        </ce:list-item>
                                    </ce:list>
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0065">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0140">Avoidance of stimuli associated with the stressor, amnesia for
                                    aspects of the trauma, as well as emotional numbness and social withdrawal.
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0070">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0145">Increased arousal (insomnia, angry outbursts, hypervigilance, poor
                                    concentration, exaggerated<ce:italic>startle response</ce:italic>).
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                        </ce:list>
                        <ce:display>
                            <ce:textbox role="alt0" id="b0025">
                                <ce:textbox-head>
                                    <ce:title>HINTS AND TIPS</ce:title>
                                </ce:textbox-head>
                                <ce:textbox-body>
                                    <ce:sections>
                                        <ce:para id="p0150">When assessing a patient with suspected PTSD, remember that
                                            head injuries and epilepsy are important differential diagnoses that may
                                            present with similar symptoms, and may also have been caused by the initial
                                            trauma. Patients with PTSD also have a high rate of comorbid substance
                                            misuse, and it is important to be vigilant for symptoms of alcohol or drug
                                            intoxication/withdrawal.
                                        </ce:para>
                                    </ce:sections>
                                </ce:textbox-body>
                            </ce:textbox>
                        </ce:display>
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0050">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0055">Dissociation</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0155">In clinical psychiatry, ‘dissociation’ describes a disruption in the usually
                        integrated functions of consciousness and cognition. In this phenomenon, memories of the past,
                        awareness of identity, thoughts, emotions, movement, sensation and/or control of behaviour
                        become separated from the rest of an individual's personality such that they function
                        independently and are not open to voluntary control.
                        <ce:cross-ref refid="f0010">Figure 12.1</ce:cross-ref>
                        describes the more common dissociative disorders.
                        <ce:display>
                            <ce:textbox role="alt0" id="b0030">
                                <ce:textbox-head>
                                    <ce:title>HINTS AND TIPS</ce:title>
                                </ce:textbox-head>
                                <ce:textbox-body>
                                    <ce:sections>
                                        <ce:para id="p0160">Depersonalization is feeling yourself to be strange or
                                            unreal. Derealization is feeling that external reality is strange or unreal.
                                            These can be considered as types of dissociation, and may be caused by
                                            psychiatric illness (e.g. depression, anxiety, schizophrenia), physical
                                            illness (e.g. epilepsy), psychosocial stress and substance abuse.
                                        </ce:para>
                                    </ce:sections>
                                </ce:textbox-body>
                            </ce:textbox>
                        </ce:display>
                    </ce:para>
                    <ce:para id="p0165">The ICD-10 requires that there be some evidence of a psychological causation
                        (stressful events or disturbed relationships) in association with the onset of the dissociative
                        symptoms. Also note that the diagnosis of dissociative disorder should not be made if there is
                        evidence of a physical or psychiatric disorder that might explain the symptoms.
                    </ce:para>
                    <ce:para id="p0170">Historically, dissociative disorders have been termed ‘hysteria’; however, this
                        term is seldom used in modern psychiatry. The term ‘conversion disorder’ is often but not always
                        used synonymously with dissociative disorders, so it is wise to clarify what exact symptoms are
                        being described if this diagnosis is encountered. Also, it is worth noting that DSM-IV
                        categorizes some dissociative disorders as somatoform disorders (see<ce:intra-ref
                                xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3863-2.00013-1" id="ia0015">Ch. 13</ce:intra-ref>).
                        <ce:display>
                            <ce:textbox role="alt0" id="b0035">
                                <ce:textbox-head>
                                    <ce:title>HINTS AND TIPS</ce:title>
                                </ce:textbox-head>
                                <ce:textbox-body>
                                    <ce:sections>
                                        <ce:para id="p0175">Before accepting the diagnosis of a dissociative disorder, a
                                            neurological affliction or other psychiatric illness should be aggressively
                                            sought for and excluded.
                                        </ce:para>
                                    </ce:sections>
                                </ce:textbox-body>
                            </ce:textbox>
                        </ce:display>
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0055">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0060">Precipitation or exacerbation of an existing mental illness
                    </ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0180">The influence of a patient's environment on their mental health cannot be
                        overemphasized. Almost all forms of mental illness (e.g. depression, psychotic illness, anxiety)
                        can be precipitated or exacerbated by psychosocial (‘life events’) or traumatic stressors.
                        However, unlike the above reactions in this group, there need not be a direct aetiological link
                        with the stressor involved.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
            </ce:section>
        </ce:section>
        <ce:section id="s0060">
            <ce:section-title id="st0065">BEREAVEMENT</ce:section-title>
            <ce:para id="p0185">Bereavement is a unique kind of stress experienced by most people during their life, and
                is considered a normal human experience. A bereavement reaction usually occurs after the loss of a loved
                person but can also result from other losses, like the loss of a national figure, or a beloved pet. The
                normal course of grief after bereavement occurs in five phases (
                <ce:cross-ref refid="f0015">Fig. 12.2</ce:cross-ref>
                <ce:float-anchor refid="f0015"/>), although these should not be regarded as a rigid sequence that is
                passed through only once.
                <ce:display>
                    <ce:textbox role="alt0" id="b0040">
                        <ce:textbox-head>
                            <ce:title>HINTS AND TIPS</ce:title>
                        </ce:textbox-head>
                        <ce:textbox-body>
                            <ce:sections>
                                <ce:para id="p0190">The length of a normal bereavement reaction is variable and tends to
                                    be longer if the death was sudden and unexpected.
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:sections>
                        </ce:textbox-body>
                    </ce:textbox>
                </ce:display>
            </ce:para>
            <ce:para id="p0195">Although most people will meet the criteria for a depressive episode at some stage
                during the grieving process, bereavement reactions are not pathological and so no psychiatric diagnosis
                should be made in these cases. However, patients who have been bereaved are at higher risk for
                developing a depressive illness requiring treatment. The DSM-IV notes the following symptoms are not
                characteristic of a normal bereavement reaction and suggest the development of a major depressive
                episode:
                <ce:list id="l0035">
                    <ce:list-item id="o0010">
                        <ce:label>1.</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0200">Guilt (other than events surrounding the death of the loved one).</ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="o0015">
                        <ce:label>2.</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0205">Suicidal ideation (other than feeling better off dead or wanting to be with
                            the deceased).
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="o0020">
                        <ce:label>3.</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0210">Preoccupation with worthlessness.</ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="o0025">
                        <ce:label>4.</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0215">Marked psychomotor retardation.</ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="o0030">
                        <ce:label>5.</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0220">Prolonged and marked functional impairment.</ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="o0035">
                        <ce:label>6.</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0225">Hallucinatory experiences (other than transiently seeing or hearing the
                            deceased).
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                </ce:list>
                If a bereavement reaction is abnormal, assess for depression. If criteria for a depressive episode are
                not met, then a diagnosis of adjustment disorder is made.
            </ce:para>
        </ce:section>
        <ce:section id="s0065">
            <ce:section-title id="st0070">DIFFERENTIAL DIAGNOSIS</ce:section-title>
            <ce:para id="p0235">The diagnosis is usually clear following thorough exploration of the nature and severity
                of both the life event and patient's reaction (see
                <ce:cross-ref refid="f0020">Fig. 12.3</ce:cross-ref>
                <ce:float-anchor refid="f0020"/>
                and
                <ce:intra-ref xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3863-2.00010-6#f0030" id="ia9500">Fig. 10.5</ce:intra-ref>
                for a diagnostic algorithm). Even if the onset of symptoms is clearly linked with a stressor, diagnosis
                of a specific major mental illness (mood disorder, psychotic disorder) should be given if diagnostic
                criteria are met, as major mental illnesses are often triggered by major stressors.
            </ce:para>
            <ce:para id="p0240">If a patient presents with psychiatric symptoms after a life-threatening event, always
                screen for features of depression as well as features of PTSD. This is because the risk of developing
                depression increases six fold in the 6 months that follow a stressful event.
            </ce:para>
        </ce:section>
        <ce:section id="s0070">
            <ce:section-title id="st0075">DISCUSSION OF CASE STUDY</ce:section-title>
            <ce:para id="p0245">Mrs PT experienced a traumatic stressor in which she believed that her physical
                integrity was under immediate threat. The event was outside the range of normal human experience and
                would have been experienced as traumatic by most people. She subsequently developed avoidance of stimuli
                associated with the trauma (avoided talking or thinking about it, avoided public transportation and
                television), amnesia for aspects of the trauma and social withdrawal. Later on, she showed signs of
                increased arousal (startle response, being ‘jumpy and quick-tempered’). Finally, Mrs PT repetitively
                re-experienced the trauma through nightmares, flashbacks and dissociation (re-living and behaving as
                though the trauma were occurring at that moment through mental imagery and hallucinations). All of the
                above suggest a diagnosis of post-traumatic stress disorder.
            </ce:para>
            <ce:para id="p0250">Now go on to
                <ce:intra-ref xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3863-2.00020-9" id="ia0020">Chapter 20</ce:intra-ref>
                to read about the anxiety disorders and their management.
            </ce:para>
        </ce:section>
    </ce:sections>
</chapter>