<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter id="c0030" version="5.3" docsubtype="chp" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.elsevier.com/xml/bk/dtd"
         xmlns:ce="http://www.elsevier.com/xml/common/dtd" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <info>
        <ce:pii>B978-0-7234-3864-9.00006-X</ce:pii>
        <ce:doi>10.1016/B978-0-7234-3864-9.00006-X</ce:doi>
        <ce:isbn>978-0-7234-3864-9</ce:isbn>
        <ce:copyright type="full-transfer" year="2015">Elsevier Ltd</ce:copyright>
    </info>
    <ce:floats>
        <ce:figure id="f0010">
            <ce:label>Fig. 6.1</ce:label>
            <ce:caption id="ca0010">
                <ce:simple-para id="sp0010">Differential diagnosis of palpitations.</ce:simple-para>
            </ce:caption>
            <ce:link locator="f06-01-9780723436331" id="lk0010"/>
        </ce:figure>
        <ce:figure id="f0015">
            <ce:label>Fig. 6.2</ce:label>
            <ce:caption id="ca0015">
                <ce:simple-para id="sp0015">Non-cardiac causes of sinus tachycardia.</ce:simple-para>
            </ce:caption>
            <ce:link locator="f06-02-9780723436331" id="lk0015"/>
        </ce:figure>
        <ce:figure id="f0020">
            <ce:label>Fig. 6.3</ce:label>
            <ce:caption id="ca0020">
                <ce:simple-para id="sp0020">Causes of sinus bradycardia.</ce:simple-para>
            </ce:caption>
            <ce:link locator="f06-03-9780723436331" id="lk0020"/>
        </ce:figure>
        <ce:figure id="f0025">
            <ce:label>Fig. 6.4</ce:label>
            <ce:caption id="ca0025">
                <ce:simple-para id="sp0025">Examining the patient with palpitations. CHB, complete heart block.
                </ce:simple-para>
            </ce:caption>
            <ce:link locator="f06-04-9780723436331" id="lk0025"/>
        </ce:figure>
    </ce:floats>
    <ce:label>6</ce:label>
    <ce:title>Palpitations</ce:title>
    <objectives>
        <ce:section-title id="st0010">Objectives</ce:section-title>
        <ce:para id="p0010">The key learning points for this chapter:
            <ce:list id="l0010">
                <ce:list-item id="u0010">
                    <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                    <ce:para id="p0015">Understand the differential diagnosis of palpitations.</ce:para>
                </ce:list-item>
                <ce:list-item id="u0015">
                    <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                    <ce:para id="p0020">Have a logical approach to assessing the patient with palpitations.</ce:para>
                </ce:list-item>
                <ce:list-item id="u0020">
                    <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                    <ce:para id="p0025">Direct investigations in a patient with palpitations.</ce:para>
                </ce:list-item>
            </ce:list>
        </ce:para>
    </objectives>
    <ce:sections>
        <ce:section id="s0010">
            <ce:section-title id="st0015">INTRODUCTION</ce:section-title>
            <ce:para id="p0030">Always check what the patient means by ‘palpitations’, or clarify what you mean by them,
                because the word means different things to different people. It is usually understood as an awareness of
                the heartbeat. The most common cause is an arrhythmia or dysrhythmia, as it is also often called,
                although other causes include conditions causing an increase in stroke volume (e.g. regurgitant valvular
                disease) or conditions causing an increase in cardiac output, often non-cardiac causes (e.g. exercise,
                thyrotoxicosis, anaemia or anxiety). If an arrhythmia is suspected, determine whether there is an
                underlying cause.
            </ce:para>
        </ce:section>
        <ce:section id="s0015">
            <ce:section-title id="st0020">DIFFERENTIAL DIAGNOSIS BY DESCRIPTION OF THE RHYTHM</ce:section-title>
            <ce:section id="s0020">
                <ce:section-title id="st0025">Regular rhythm</ce:section-title>
                <ce:para id="p0035">The differential diagnosis of regular palpitations (
                    <ce:cross-ref refid="f0010">Fig. 6.1</ce:cross-ref>
                    <ce:float-anchor refid="f0010"/>) includes the following:
                    <ce:list id="l0015">
                        <ce:list-item id="u0025">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0040">Heavy heartbeats with normal rate: most often cardiac consciousness with
                                sinus rhythm. It tends to be worse at rest, especially when in bed at night and during
                                periods of stress.
                            </ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                        <ce:list-item id="u0030">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0045">Fast heart rate: sinus tachycardia, atrial flutter with block,
                                supraventricular tachycardia or ventricular tachycardia.
                            </ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                        <ce:list-item id="u0035">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0050">Bursts of fast beats: paroxysmal atrial tachycardia. There is often a
                                very long history dating back years with a single attack followed by a long interval
                                before the next attack. Other causes include atrial flutter, junctional rhythm or
                                ventricular tachycardia.
                            </ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                        <ce:list-item id="u0040">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0055">Slow heart rate: sinus bradycardia, atrioventricular block.</ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                    </ce:list>
                </ce:para>
            </ce:section>
            <ce:section id="s0025">
                <ce:section-title id="st0030">Irregular rhythm</ce:section-title>
                <ce:para id="p0060">The differential diagnosis of irregular palpitations (<ce:cross-ref refid="f0010">
                    Fig. 6.1</ce:cross-ref>) includes the following:
                    <ce:list id="l0020">
                        <ce:list-item id="u0045">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0065">Missed beats, ‘thumps’: multiple ectopics from the atrium or ventricle.
                                The symptoms are more troublesome at rest and may disappear during exercise.
                            </ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                        <ce:list-item id="u0050">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0070">Fast (or normal if treated): atrial flutter with variable block, atrial
                                fibrillation (persistent irregularity with exercise), and multiple premature beats with
                                sinus tachycardia.
                            </ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                    </ce:list>
                </ce:para>
            </ce:section>
        </ce:section>
        <ce:section id="s0030">
            <ce:section-title id="st0035">HISTORY</ce:section-title>
            <ce:para id="p0075">A careful history of the palpitations will often lead to the correct diagnosis,
                especially as between episodes examination and investigations may be unremarkable. Are they continuous
                or intermittent? Are they fast, normal rate or slow? Are they regular or irregular? When did the
                palpitations start? This can vary from a few minutes to decades. Generally, if the onset dates back
                years and there have been no serious complications (e.g. syncope) the palpitations are usually benign.
            </ce:para>
            <ce:para id="p0080">How often do the palpitations occur and how long do they last for? They may last for
                days or seconds, with intervals between episodes of a few hours to years. Has the patient learned any
                manoeuvres to terminate the attacks? Enquire about the patient's concerns as they may fear serious
                underlying cardiac disease, although there is often a benign cause. Are there any associated features?
                These may be related to the underlying cause (e.g. angina, features of hyperthyroidism) or be a
                consequence of the palpitations (e.g. dizziness or syncope).
                <ce:display>
                    <ce:textbox role="alt0" id="b0010">
                        <ce:textbox-head>
                            <ce:title>HINTS AND TIPS</ce:title>
                        </ce:textbox-head>
                        <ce:textbox-body>
                            <ce:sections>
                                <ce:para id="p0085">Ask the patient to tap out their heart rhythm on the desktop. This
                                    will often give a good guide to diagnosis.
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:sections>
                        </ce:textbox-body>
                    </ce:textbox>
                </ce:display>
            </ce:para>
            <ce:section id="s0035">
                <ce:section-title id="st0040">Causes and contributing factors</ce:section-title>
                <ce:para id="p0090">Ask about smoking, alcohol, work, stress, caffeine (tea, coffee, cola) intake and
                    any illegal drug use. These may contribute to extrasystoles.
                </ce:para>
                <ce:para id="p0095">A history of ischaemic and valvular heart disease (including previous rheumatic
                    fever) should be sought. This needs to be made prominent in the PMH as structural heart problems
                    will predispose to pathological arrhythmias.
                </ce:para>
                <ce:para id="p0100">A family history of palpitations or sudden cardiac death may be important (e.g.
                    hypertrophic obstructive cardiomyopathy or long QT syndromes).
                </ce:para>
                <ce:para id="p0105">A full drug history of both prescribed and over-the-counter medications is
                    essential. Remember, many drugs, both cardiac and non-cardiac, can promote palpitations. Most
                    anti-arrhythmic drugs are also potentially pro-arrhythmic.
                </ce:para>
                <ce:para id="p0110">Non-cardiac causes of sinus tachycardia and causes of sinus bradycardia are outlined
                    in
                    <ce:cross-ref refid="f0015">Figs 6.2</ce:cross-ref>
                    <ce:float-anchor refid="f0015"/>
                    and
                    <ce:cross-ref refid="f0020">6.3</ce:cross-ref>
                    <ce:float-anchor refid="f0020"/>, respectively.
                </ce:para>
                <ce:para id="p0115">Non-cardiac causes of palpitations include the following:
                    <ce:list id="l0025">
                        <ce:list-item id="u0055">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0120">Thyrotoxicosis: may cause sinus tachycardia, paroxysmal atrial
                                tachycardia, and atrial flutter/fibrillation.
                            </ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                        <ce:list-item id="u0060">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0125">Hypothyroidism (myxedema): may be responsible for sinus bradycardia.
                            </ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                        <ce:list-item id="u0065">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0130">Anxiety: a very common cause of palpitations.</ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                    </ce:list>
                </ce:para>
            </ce:section>
        </ce:section>
        <ce:section id="s0040">
            <ce:section-title id="st0045">CONSEQUENCES OF PALPITATIONS</ce:section-title>
            <ce:para id="p0135">Palpitations can cause a range of problems, from minor anxiety to syncope or sudden
                death. This accounts for much of the patient's concern. If a benign arrhythmia is present, reassurance
                that the condition is not serious is often all that is required. Changes in rate may be more serious,
                compromising coronary blood supply and leading to symptoms of myocardial ischaemia or cardiac failure.
            </ce:para>
            <ce:para id="p0140">Tachycardia or bradycardia may lead to a reduction in cardiac output and cause dizziness
                or collapse (e.g. Stokes–Adams attacks in complete heart block). Ventricular tachycardia is potentially
                life-threatening.
            </ce:para>
        </ce:section>
        <ce:section id="s0045">
            <ce:section-title id="st0050">EXAMINING THE PATIENT WITH PALPITATIONS</ce:section-title>
            <ce:para id="p0145">A guide to examining the patient with palpitations is given in
                <ce:cross-ref refid="f0025">Fig. 6.4</ce:cross-ref>
                <ce:float-anchor refid="f0025"/>. Look for signs of systemic diseases. Next feel the pulse. Note the
                following:
                <ce:list id="l0030">
                    <ce:list-item id="u0070">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0150">Rate: beats per minute.</ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0075">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0155">Rhythm: regular, regularly irregular (e.g. Wenckebach second-degree heart
                            block), irregularly irregular: e.g. multiple ectopic beats or atrial fibrillation.
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0080">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0160">Volume/character: e.g. a collapsing pulse of hyperdynamic circulation or a
                            low-volume pulse of shock or aortic stenosis. Remember this may be positional, so raising
                            the arm above the heart may exaggerate a collapsing pulse.
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                </ce:list>
            </ce:para>
            <ce:para id="p0165">If the patient is symptom-free at the time of examination, the pulse may be normal.
            </ce:para>
            <ce:para id="p0170">The blood pressure will be low if the arrhythmia leads to a reduction in cardiac output.
                Hypertension may predispose to atrial fibrillation.
            </ce:para>
            <ce:para id="p0175">The jugular venous pressure may be elevated if cardiac failure is present. Irregular
                cannon ‘a’ waves are visible with complete heart block, and ‘a’ waves are absent in atrial fibrillation.
            </ce:para>
            <ce:para id="p0180">A displaced apex may indicate cardiomyopathy. Feel for heaves and thrills with
                associated right ventricular enlargement and valvular heart disease. Assess the rate and rhythm by
                auscultation. The pulse rate felt at the radial artery may be slower than the apical rate in atrial
                fibrillation (pulse deficit). Listen for cardiac murmurs (e.g. evidence of mitral valve disease, mitral
                valve prolapse). Focus on any abnormal findings (see<ce:intra-ref
                        xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00030-7" id="ia0010">Ch. 30</ce:intra-ref>).
                <ce:display>
                    <ce:textbox role="alt0" id="b0015">
                        <ce:textbox-head>
                            <ce:title>HINTS AND TIPS</ce:title>
                        </ce:textbox-head>
                        <ce:textbox-body>
                            <ce:sections>
                                <ce:para id="p0185">An irregularly irregular pulse (atrial fibrillation) is irregular in
                                    BOTH rhythm AND volume.
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:sections>
                        </ce:textbox-body>
                    </ce:textbox>
                </ce:display>
            </ce:para>
        </ce:section>
        <ce:section id="s0050">
            <ce:section-title id="st0055">INVESTIGATING THE PATIENT WITH PALPITATIONS</ce:section-title>
            <ce:para id="p0190">The following tests should be performed.</ce:para>
            <ce:section id="s0055">
                <ce:section-title id="st0060">Vital signs</ce:section-title>
                <ce:para id="p0195">
                    <ce:list id="l0035">
                        <ce:list-item id="u0085">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0200">Pulse, blood pressure, respiratory rate and saturations.</ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                        <ce:list-item id="u0090">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0205">Pulse oximetry.</ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                    </ce:list>
                </ce:para>
            </ce:section>
            <ce:section id="s0060">
                <ce:section-title id="st0065">Blood tests</ce:section-title>
                <ce:para id="p0210">
                    <ce:list id="l0040">
                        <ce:list-item id="u0095">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0215">Full blood count: anaemia.</ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                        <ce:list-item id="u0100">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0220">Urea and electrolytes: disturbances of potassium or, less commonly,
                                magnesium and calcium may contribute to refractory arrhythmias.
                            </ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                        <ce:list-item id="u0105">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0225">Thyroid function tests: hypo/hyperthyroidism.</ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                        <ce:list-item id="u0110">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0230">Drug concentration if appropriate (e.g. digoxin levels in suspected
                                toxicity).
                            </ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                    </ce:list>
                </ce:para>
            </ce:section>
            <ce:section id="s0065">
                <ce:section-title id="st0070">Other tests</ce:section-title>
                <ce:para id="p0235">
                    <ce:list id="l0045">
                        <ce:list-item id="u0115">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0240">12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG): although mandatory for everyone with
                                palpitations, this test rarely provides the diagnosis as it is unlikely that they will
                                be caught on a resting 12-lead ECG. Wolff–Parkinson–White syndrome will be seen at rest,
                                as will atrial fibrillation. Ectopic beats may be seen. Careful analysis of the QRS
                                morphology and QT interval, etc., may be important.
                            </ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                        <ce:list-item id="u0120">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0245">24-h ECG: for intermittent symptoms. It should be carried out with a
                                diary of symptoms to see if they correlate with any rhythm disturbances found.
                            </ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                        <ce:list-item id="u0125">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0250">Echocardiogram: to exclude any underlying structural heart disease.
                            </ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                        <ce:list-item id="u0130">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0255">‘Cardiomemo’: if symptoms do not occur every day, a ‘cardiomemo’ can
                                record the heart rhythm at the press of a button.
                            </ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                        <ce:list-item id="u0135">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0260">Exercise test: the induction of symptoms under controlled conditions
                                with ECG monitoring may be appropriate.
                            </ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                        <ce:list-item id="u0140">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0265">Electrophysiological studies: more rarely, patients may be referred for
                                specialized studies. These can be used to induce arrhythmias, locate the origin of any
                                arrhythmic foci, assess the response to drug treatment or destroy any aberrant pathway
                                via radiofrequency ablation.
                            </ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                    </ce:list>
                    <ce:display>
                        <ce:textbox role="alt0" id="b0020">
                            <ce:textbox-head>
                                <ce:title>HINTS AND TIPS</ce:title>
                            </ce:textbox-head>
                            <ce:textbox-body>
                                <ce:sections>
                                    <ce:para id="p0270">Atrial fibrillation with a fast ventricular response (‘fast AF’)
                                        is easily confused with a regular tachycardia when assessing the pulse.
                                    </ce:para>
                                </ce:sections>
                            </ce:textbox-body>
                        </ce:textbox>
                    </ce:display>
                </ce:para>
            </ce:section>
        </ce:section>
    </ce:sections>
</chapter>