<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter id="c0130" version="5.2" docsubtype="chp" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.elsevier.com/xml/bk/dtd"
         xmlns:ce="http://www.elsevier.com/xml/common/dtd" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <info>
        <ce:pii>B978-0-7234-3863-2.00026-X</ce:pii>
        <ce:doi>10.1016/B978-0-7234-3863-2.00026-X</ce:doi>
        <ce:isbn>978-0-7234-3863-2</ce:isbn>
        <ce:copyright type="full-transfer" year="2015">Elsevier Ltd</ce:copyright>
    </info>
    <ce:floats>
        <ce:figure id="f0010">
            <ce:label>Fig. 26.1</ce:label>
            <ce:caption>
                <ce:simple-para id="sp0010" role="caption">Prevalence of mental illness in people over the age of 65
                </ce:simple-para>
            </ce:caption>
            <ce:link locator="f26-01-9780723436362" id="lk0010"/>
        </ce:figure>
        <ce:figure id="f0015">
            <ce:label>Fig. 26.2</ce:label>
            <ce:caption>
                <ce:simple-para id="sp0015">Age-related changes in drug handling and effects</ce:simple-para>
            </ce:caption>
            <ce:link locator="f26-02-9780723436362" id="lk0015"/>
        </ce:figure>
    </ce:floats>
    <ce:label>26</ce:label>
    <ce:title>Older adult psychiatry</ce:title>
    <objectives>
        <ce:section-title id="st0010">Objectives</ce:section-title>
        <ce:para id="p0010">After this chapter you should have an understanding of:
            <ce:list id="l0010">
                <ce:list-item id="u0010">
                    <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                    <ce:para id="p0015">The most prevalent psychiatric disorders in people over the age of 65</ce:para>
                </ce:list-item>
                <ce:list-item id="u0015">
                    <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                    <ce:para id="p0020">Which features are particularly prominent in depression in older adults
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:list-item>
                <ce:list-item id="u0020">
                    <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                    <ce:para id="p0025">The dangers of prescribing tricyclic antidepressants to older adults</ce:para>
                </ce:list-item>
                <ce:list-item id="u0025">
                    <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                    <ce:para id="p0030">How late-onset schizophrenia differs from early-onset schizophrenia</ce:para>
                </ce:list-item>
                <ce:list-item id="u0030">
                    <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                    <ce:para id="p0035">The role of home assessments in older adult psychiatry</ce:para>
                </ce:list-item>
                <ce:list-item id="u0035">
                    <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                    <ce:para id="p0040">Factors to consider before prescribing a benzodiazepine to an older adult
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:list-item>
            </ce:list>
        </ce:para>
    </objectives>
    <ce:sections>
        <ce:para id="p0045">The most common psychiatric disorders in older adults are dementia and delirium (see
            <ce:intra-ref xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3863-2.00025-8" id="ia0010">Ch. 25</ce:intra-ref>). This chapter
            considers other psychiatric disorders in older adults.
        </ce:para>
        <ce:para id="p0050">Patients arbitrarily come under the care of older adult psychiatrists at the age of 65
            years, as it is the average age of retirement. Services for older adults face a huge increase in demand over
            coming decades. Currently, one in six of the UK population is aged over 65 but by 2050 one in four people
            are projected to be over 65. The number of ‘very old’ (aged over 80) is set to almost triple by 2050.
        </ce:para>
        <ce:para id="p0055">Ageing is associated with an increased prevalence of both mental and physical health
            problems. Older adults may also face new social challenges such as coming to terms with retirement; income
            reduction; living alone or being separated from family; death of spouse, siblings and peers; and coping with
            deteriorating physical health and mobility.
        </ce:para>
        <ce:section id="s0010">
            <ce:section-title id="st0015">MENTAL ILLNESS IN OLDER ADULTS</ce:section-title>
            <ce:section id="s0015">
                <ce:section-title id="st0020">Epidemiology</ce:section-title>
                <ce:para id="p0060">The prevalence of all mental illness tends to increase with age and is about 25–30%
                    in people over the age of 65. The prevalence of mental illness tends to be higher in residential
                    homes.
                    <ce:cross-ref refid="f0010">Figure 26.1</ce:cross-ref>
                    <ce:float-anchor refid="f0010"/>
                    summarizes the prevalence of the individual psychiatric disorders in older adults.
                </ce:para>
            </ce:section>
            <ce:section id="s0020">
                <ce:section-title id="st0025">Depressive disorders</ce:section-title>
                <ce:para id="p0065">Depression in older adults presents similarly to that in younger people, although
                    certain features seem more prevalent:
                    <ce:list id="l0015">
                        <ce:list-item id="u0040">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0070">Severe psychomotor agitation or retardation.</ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                        <ce:list-item id="u0045">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0075">Cognitive impairment (‘depressive pseudodementia’).</ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                        <ce:list-item id="u0050">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0080">Poor concentration.</ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                        <ce:list-item id="u0055">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0085">Generalized anxiety.</ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                        <ce:list-item id="u0060">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0090">Excessive concerns about physical health (hypochondriasis).</ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                        <ce:list-item id="u0065">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0095">When psychotic, older adults are particularly likely to have
                                hypochondriacal delusions, delusions of poverty and nihilistic delusions (see
                                <ce:intra-ref id="ia9000" xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3863-2.00009-X#p0415">p.
                                    69</ce:intra-ref>).
                            </ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                    </ce:list>
                    Depression is often under-diagnosed in older adults, so a high index of suspicion is needed. This is
                    important considering that older adults are at high risk for completed suicide, even though the
                    prevalence of self-harm in this group is lower than in younger adults.
                    <ce:display>
                        <ce:textbox role="alt0" id="b0010">
                            <ce:textbox-head>
                                <ce:title>HINTS AND TIPS</ce:title>
                            </ce:textbox-head>
                            <ce:textbox-body>
                                <ce:sections>
                                    <ce:para id="p0105">Self-harm in an older adult should be considered to be with
                                        suicidal intent until proven otherwise.
                                    </ce:para>
                                </ce:sections>
                            </ce:textbox-body>
                        </ce:textbox>
                    </ce:display>
                </ce:para>
                <ce:para id="p0110">The principles of treatment are the same as for younger adults, although medication
                    should be introduced cautiously as older adults have an increased risk of developing adverse
                    side-effects and generally need lower doses. Tricyclic antidepressants should be avoided if possible
                    as postural hypotension and cognitive impairment are very common side-effects in older adults.
                    Response to antidepressants is often slower in older adults, with benefits taking 6–8 weeks to
                    emerge.
                </ce:para>
                <ce:para id="p0115">Electroconvulsive therapy (ECT) is a very effective treatment for depression in this
                    population group and should be considered for severe depression, suicidal ideation, severe
                    psychomotor retardation, failure to respond to or tolerate medication and previous good response to
                    ECT. Lithium augmentation may be used in treatment-resistant cases, although the dose is generally
                    lower than that used in younger adults. Patients in this age group often need lifelong
                    antidepressant treatment to reduce the chance of relapse. Psychosocial intervention in the form of
                    social support and possibly cognitive-behavioural therapy are also important.
                </ce:para>
                <ce:para id="p0120">Poor prognostic factors include comorbid physical illness, late detection of illness
                    and poor concordance with antidepressant medication. Depressed older adults have a higher mortality
                    than the non-depressed do, even when physical illness is taken into account.
                    <ce:display>
                        <ce:textbox role="alt0" id="b0015">
                            <ce:textbox-head>
                                <ce:title>HINTS AND TIPS</ce:title>
                            </ce:textbox-head>
                            <ce:textbox-body>
                                <ce:sections>
                                    <ce:para id="p0125">Cotard's syndrome describes the presence of nihilistic and
                                        hypochondriacal delusions as part of a depressive psychosis and is typically
                                        seen in older adults.
                                    </ce:para>
                                </ce:sections>
                            </ce:textbox-body>
                        </ce:textbox>
                    </ce:display>
                </ce:para>
            </ce:section>
            <ce:section id="s0025">
                <ce:section-title id="st0030">Mania</ce:section-title>
                <ce:para id="p0130">Unlike depression, the incidence of bipolar affective disorder does not increase
                    with age, although late onset cases seem to be less influenced by genetic factors (fewer of these
                    patients have positive family histories for mood disorders). In a fifth of cases, mania is
                    precipitated by an acute medical condition, e.g. stroke or myocardial infarction. The presentation
                    and treatment is similar to that of younger adults.
                </ce:para>
            </ce:section>
            <ce:section id="s0030">
                <ce:section-title id="st0035">Late-onset schizophrenia (late paraphrenia)</ce:section-title>
                <ce:para id="p0135">Older adult psychiatrists in the UK use the term
                    <ce:italic>late-onset schizophrenia</ce:italic>
                    or
                    <ce:italic>late paraphrenia</ce:italic>
                    to denote a group of patients who develop psychotic symptoms late in life, usually over the age of
                    60. Late-onset schizophrenia is characterized predominantly by delusional thinking, usually of a
                    persecutory or grandiose nature. These delusions tend not to be as bizarre as they sometimes are in
                    earlier onset schizophrenia (e.g. rather than believing that secret agents are monitoring them by
                    satellite, a patient with paraphrenia may assert that the neighbours have been poisoning their water
                    supply). Hallucinations may occur but disorganized thinking, inappropriate affect and catatonic
                    features almost never feature.
                </ce:para>
                <ce:para id="p0140">The aetiology of late-onset schizophrenia seems different to early-onset
                    schizophrenia in that sufferers are less likely to have a family history of schizophrenia. Also,
                    late-onset schizophrenia is far more common in women than men – unlike early-onset schizophrenia,
                    which is slightly more likely to arise in men. Sensory deprivation, particularly hearing loss and
                    social isolation, is also implicated in its aetiology.
                </ce:para>
                <ce:para id="p0145">The treatment is with antipsychotics but some work is needed in building up a
                    therapeutic relationship as these patients are often difficult to engage and poor concordance is
                    associated with a poor treatment response. Note that although late-onset schizophrenia does seem to
                    be a distinct entity, it is not a term used by the ICD-10 or DSM-IV; here, these patients would be
                    classified as having schizophrenia or delusional disorder.
                    <ce:display>
                        <ce:textbox role="alt0" id="b0020">
                            <ce:textbox-head>
                                <ce:title>HINTS AND TIPS</ce:title>
                            </ce:textbox-head>
                            <ce:textbox-body>
                                <ce:sections>
                                    <ce:para id="p0150">Diogenes' syndrome, or ‘senile squalor’, is the term used to
                                        describe an elderly recluse who lives in a state of perpetual filth and gross
                                        self-neglect, often with the hoarding of rubbish. This is purely a descriptive
                                        term and may occur in individuals with alcohol abuse, frontal lobe dysfunction,
                                        personality disorder and chronic psychotic illness. It may also occur at a
                                        younger age.
                                    </ce:para>
                                </ce:sections>
                            </ce:textbox-body>
                        </ce:textbox>
                    </ce:display>
                </ce:para>
            </ce:section>
        </ce:section>
        <ce:section id="s0035">
            <ce:section-title id="st0040">ASSESSMENT CONSIDERATIONS IN OLDER ADULTS</ce:section-title>
            <ce:para id="p0155">
                <ce:list id="l0020">
                    <ce:list-item id="u0070">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0160">Home assessments are a very important part of older adult psychiatry.
                            Patients can be assessed in their normal environment and collateral information can be
                            obtained from family members. It is important to ascertain whether the patient can be
                            managed at home (i.e. risk of harm to self and others; ability to carry out activities of
                            daily living (ADL), drive, manage financial affairs, etc.), or whether additional community
                            support or hospitalization is needed.
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0075">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0165">Collateral information from the patient's general practitioner (GP), family
                            and neighbours is an important part of history taking.
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0080">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0170">Mental state examination follows the same format as for all adults, although
                            extra consideration should be given to the assessment of cognitive functioning and it is
                            advisable to always do a standardized test, e.g. a Mini-Mental State Examination. (see
                            <ce:intra-ref xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3863-2.00014-3#f0065" id="ia0015">Fig. 14.12
                            </ce:intra-ref>
                            for alternatives).
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0085">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0175">A thorough physical examination is very important. Do not forget to assess
                            hearing and vision as well as tremors and involuntary movements.
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0090">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0180">Routine investigations in the newly diagnosed or hospitalized older adult
                            include: full blood count, urea and electrolytes, liver function tests, thyroid function
                            tests, calcium, glucose, urinalysis (with mid-stream urine microscopy and culture if
                            indicated), chest X-ray, electrocardiogram (ECG) and consideration of serum magnesium,
                            phosphate, vitamin B
                            <ce:inf>12</ce:inf>
                            and folate and a CT or MRI head. Remember that the chances of a physical illness causing or
                            aggravating a mental deterioration are significant in older adults.
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                </ce:list>
            </ce:para>
        </ce:section>
        <ce:section id="s0040">
            <ce:section-title id="st0045">TREATMENT CONSIDERATIONS IN OLDER ADULTS</ce:section-title>
            <ce:section id="s0045">
                <ce:section-title id="st0050">Physiological changes with ageing</ce:section-title>
                <ce:para id="p0185">There are a number of physiological changes that occur with ageing, which may affect
                    the way the body handles certain drugs.
                    <ce:cross-ref refid="f0015">Figure 26.2</ce:cross-ref>
                    <ce:float-anchor refid="f0015"/>
                    describes the most important changes and their effects. The net result of these changes is that the
                    tissue concentration of a drug may be increased by over 50%, especially in malnourished, dehydrated
                    and debilitated patients. Therefore the adage, ‘start low and go slow’ applies especially to the use
                    of psychotropic drugs in the older adult.
                </ce:para>
                <ce:section id="s0050">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0055">Polypharmacy</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0190">Those aged over 65 receive 45% of all prescriptions issued in the UK and many of
                        these are for five drugs or more. This increases the risk of adverse reactions, drug
                        interactions and poor concordance. Prescribing psychotropic drugs for common symptoms such as
                        insomnia and headache should be avoided as they may lead to further non-specific symptoms, e.g.
                        confusion, drowsiness and light-headedness. Medication should not be a substitute for adequate
                        social care, the lack of which often underlies many of these symptoms.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0055">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0060">Concordance</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0195">Concordance is often a problem in older adults, especially with those who are
                        visually impaired, cognitively impaired, take numerous drugs and live alone. This may be
                        improved by simplifying medication regimens, taking time to explain dosing schedules, using
                        large font prescription labels or concordance aids such as dosette boxes. Organizing supervision
                        of medication taking by a relative, friend or support worker may be necessary.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0060">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0065">Psychosocial interventions</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0200">Psychological treatments, such as cognitive-behavioural therapy can be used with
                        success in older adults as with younger adults. Reality orientation and reminiscence therapies
                        have been used to reduce disorientation and stimulate remote memories in patients with dementia.
                        Practical psychosocial interventions such as memory aids (e.g. notebooks, calendars) and
                        assistance with mobility and daily activities by a support worker should not be underestimated.
                        Occupational therapy assessment of activities of daily living (ADL), which assess skills such as
                        washing, dressing, eating, shopping, etc., give carers an indication of patients' strengths and
                        weaknesses and enable a care package to be tailored that caters specifically for these.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
            </ce:section>
        </ce:section>
    </ce:sections>
</chapter>