<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter id="c0045" version="5.2" docsubtype="chp" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.elsevier.com/xml/bk/dtd"
         xmlns:ce="http://www.elsevier.com/xml/common/dtd" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <info>
        <ce:pii>B978-0-7234-3863-2.00009-X</ce:pii>
        <ce:doi>10.1016/B978-0-7234-3863-2.00009-X</ce:doi>
        <ce:isbn>978-0-7234-3863-2</ce:isbn>
        <ce:copyright type="full-transfer" year="2015">Elsevier Ltd</ce:copyright>
    </info>
    <ce:floats>
        <ce:figure id="f0010">
            <ce:label>Fig. 9.1</ce:label>
            <ce:caption>
                <ce:simple-para id="sp0010" role="caption">Outline of classification of hallucinations</ce:simple-para>
            </ce:caption>
            <ce:link locator="f09-01-9780723436362" id="lk0010"/>
        </ce:figure>
        <ce:figure id="f0015">
            <ce:label>Fig. 9.2</ce:label>
            <ce:caption>
                <ce:simple-para id="sp0015" role="caption">Classification of delusions by content</ce:simple-para>
            </ce:caption>
            <ce:link locator="f09-02-9780723436362" id="lk0015"/>
        </ce:figure>
        <ce:figure id="f0020">
            <ce:label>Fig. 9.3</ce:label>
            <ce:caption>
                <ce:simple-para id="sp0020" role="caption">Thought disorder: simplified representation</ce:simple-para>
            </ce:caption>
            <ce:link locator="f09-03-9780723436362" id="lk0020"/>
        </ce:figure>
        <ce:figure id="f0025">
            <ce:label>Fig. 9.4</ce:label>
            <ce:caption>
                <ce:simple-para id="sp0025" role="caption">Motor symptoms in schizophrenia</ce:simple-para>
            </ce:caption>
            <ce:link locator="f09-04-9780723436362" id="lk0025"/>
        </ce:figure>
        <ce:figure id="f0030">
            <ce:label>Fig. 9.5</ce:label>
            <ce:caption>
                <ce:simple-para id="sp0030" role="caption">Differential diagnosis for the psychotic patient
                </ce:simple-para>
            </ce:caption>
            <ce:link locator="f09-05-9780723436362" id="lk0030"/>
        </ce:figure>
        <ce:figure id="f0035">
            <ce:label>Fig. 9.6</ce:label>
            <ce:caption>
                <ce:simple-para id="sp0035" role="caption">ICD-10 diagnostic guidelines for schizophrenia
                </ce:simple-para>
            </ce:caption>
            <ce:link locator="f09-06-9780723436362" id="lk0035"/>
        </ce:figure>
        <ce:figure id="f0040">
            <ce:label>Fig. 9.7</ce:label>
            <ce:caption>
                <ce:simple-para id="sp0040" role="caption">Schneider's first-rank symptoms of schizophrenia
                </ce:simple-para>
            </ce:caption>
            <ce:link locator="f09-07-9780723436362" id="lk0040"/>
        </ce:figure>
        <ce:figure id="f0045">
            <ce:label>Fig. 9.8</ce:label>
            <ce:caption>
                <ce:simple-para id="sp0045" role="caption">Medical and substance-related causes of psychotic symptoms
                </ce:simple-para>
            </ce:caption>
            <ce:link locator="f09-08-9780723436362" id="lk0045"/>
        </ce:figure>
        <ce:figure id="f0050">
            <ce:label>Fig. 9.9</ce:label>
            <ce:caption>
                <ce:simple-para id="sp0050" role="caption">Algorithm for the diagnosis of a patient presenting with
                    psychotic symptoms
                </ce:simple-para>
            </ce:caption>
            <ce:link locator="f09-09-9780723436362" id="lk0050"/>
        </ce:figure>
    </ce:floats>
    <ce:label>9</ce:label>
    <ce:title>The psychotic patient</ce:title>
    <objectives>
        <ce:section-title id="st0010">Objectives</ce:section-title>
        <ce:para id="p0105">After this chapter you should have an understanding of:
            <ce:list id="l0105">
                <ce:list-item id="u0060">
                    <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                    <ce:para id="p0110">The definition of psychosis</ce:para>
                </ce:list-item>
                <ce:list-item id="u0065">
                    <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                    <ce:para id="p0115">The definitions of: hallucination, pseudohallucination and illusion</ce:para>
                </ce:list-item>
                <ce:list-item id="u0070">
                    <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                    <ce:para id="p0120">The definitions of: delusion, overvalued idea and obsession</ce:para>
                </ce:list-item>
                <ce:list-item id="u0075">
                    <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                    <ce:para id="p0125">The phenomenology of psychosis</ce:para>
                </ce:list-item>
                <ce:list-item id="u0080">
                    <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                    <ce:para id="p0130">The differential diagnosis of psychosis</ce:para>
                </ce:list-item>
                <ce:list-item id="u0085">
                    <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                    <ce:para id="p0135">How to assess someone presenting with psychotic features</ce:para>
                </ce:list-item>
            </ce:list>
        </ce:para>
    </objectives>
    <ce:sections>
        <ce:para id="p0140">
            <ce:display>
                <ce:textbox role="alt2" id="b0010">
                    <ce:textbox-head>
                        <ce:title>Case summary</ce:title>
                    </ce:textbox-head>
                    <ce:textbox-body>
                        <ce:sections>
                            <ce:para id="p0145">Mr PP, aged 23 years, was assessed by his general practitioner (GP)
                                because his family had become concerned about his behaviour. Over the last 6 months his
                                college attendance had been uncharacteristically poor and he had terminated his
                                part-time work. He had also become increasingly reclusive, spending more time alone in
                                his flat, refusing to answer the door or see his friends. After some inappropriate
                                suspiciousness, he allowed the GP into his flat and then disclosed that government
                                scientists had started to perform experiments on him over the last year. These involved
                                the insertion of an electrode into his brain that detected gamma rays transmitted from
                                government headquarters, which issued him with commands and ‘planted’ strange ideas in
                                his head. When the GP asked how he knew this, he replied that he heard the ‘men's
                                voices’ as ‘clear as day’ and that they continually commented on what he was thinking.
                                He explained that his suspicion that ‘all was not right’ was confirmed when he heard the
                                neighbour's dog barking in the middle of the night – at that point he knew ‘for certain’
                                that he was being interfered with. Prompted by the GP, Mr PP also mentioned that a man
                                in his local pub knew of his plight and had sent him a ‘covert signal’ when he overheard
                                the man conversing about the dangers of nuclear experiments. He also admitted to
                                ‘receiving coded information’ from the radio whenever it was turned on. The GP found no
                                evidence of abnormal mood, incoherence of speech or disturbed motor function. Mr PP
                                denied use of illicit drugs and appeared physically well. After the GP discussed the
                                case with a psychiatrist, Mr PP was admitted to a psychiatric hospital. He agreed to a
                                voluntary admission, as he was now afraid of staying alone at home.
                            </ce:para>
                            <ce:para id="p0150">
                                <ce:italic>(For a discussion of the case study see the end of the chapter)</ce:italic>
                            </ce:para>
                        </ce:sections>
                    </ce:textbox-body>
                </ce:textbox>
            </ce:display>
        </ce:para>
        <ce:para id="p0155">The psychotic patient can present in many varied ways. It is often very difficult to elicit
            and describe specific symptoms when a patient is speaking or behaving in a grossly disorganized fashion.
            Therefore, it is important to approach the psychotic patient in a logical and systematic fashion as well as
            to have a good understanding of the psychopathology involved.
        </ce:para>
        <ce:section id="s0010">
            <ce:section-title id="st0015">DEFINITIONS AND CLINICAL FEATURES</ce:section-title>
            <ce:para id="p0160">Psychosis refers to a mental state in which reality is grossly distorted, resulting in
                symptoms such as delusions, hallucinations and thought disorder. However, patients with schizophrenia
                and other psychotic disorders often have other symptoms too, e.g. psychomotor abnormalities, mood/affect
                disturbance, cognitive deficits and disorganized behaviour.
            </ce:para>
            <ce:para id="p0165">There are many classifications that attempt to describe all the symptoms seen in
                schizophrenia and psychosis. So, in order to simplify matters it is useful to approach psychotic
                psychopathology using five somewhat interrelated parameters:
                <ce:list id="l0110">
                    <ce:list-item id="o0055">
                        <ce:label>1.</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0170">Perception.</ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="o0060">
                        <ce:label>2.</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0175">Abnormal beliefs.</ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="o0065">
                        <ce:label>3.</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0180">Thought disorder.</ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="o0070">
                        <ce:label>4.</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0185">Negative symptoms.</ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="o0075">
                        <ce:label>5.</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0190">Psychomotor function.</ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                </ce:list>
            </ce:para>
            <ce:section id="s0015">
                <ce:section-title id="st0020">Perceptual disturbance</ce:section-title>
                <ce:para id="p0195">
                    <ce:italic>Perception</ce:italic>
                    is the process of making sense of the physical information we receive from our five sensory
                    modalities.
                </ce:para>
                <ce:para id="p0200">
                    <ce:italic>Hallucinations</ce:italic>
                    are perceptions occurring in the absence of an external physical stimulus, which have the following
                    important characteristics:
                    <ce:list id="l0115">
                        <ce:list-item id="u0090">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0205">To the patient, the nature of a hallucination is exactly the same as a
                                normal sensory experience – i.e. it appears real. Therefore, patients often have little
                                insight into their abnormal experience.
                            </ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                        <ce:list-item id="u0095">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0210">They are experienced as external sensations from any one of the five
                                sensory modalities (hearing, vision, smell, taste, touch) and should be distinguished
                                from ideas, thoughts, images or fantasies which originate in the patient's own mind.
                            </ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                        <ce:list-item id="u0100">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0215">They occur without an external stimulus and are not merely distortions
                                of an existing physical stimulus (see illusions).
                            </ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                    </ce:list>
                    <ce:italic>Illusions</ce:italic>
                    are misperceptions of real external stimuli, e.g. in a dark room, a dressing gown hanging on a
                    bedroom wall is perceived as a person. Illusions often occur in healthy people and are usually
                    associated with inattention or strong emotion.
                </ce:para>
                <ce:para id="p0225">A
                    <ce:italic>pseudohallucination</ce:italic>
                    is a perceptual experience which differs from a hallucination in that it appears to arise in the
                    subjective inner space of the mind, not through one of the external sensory organs. Patients tend to
                    describe these sensations as being perceived with the ‘inner eye’ or ‘mind's eye’ (or ear). Although
                    experienced in internal space they are not under conscious control. Examples include: distressing
                    flashbacks in post-traumatic stress disorder or someone hearing a voice inside their own head
                    telling them to harm themselves. These are not viewed as true psychotic experiences. Note that some
                    psychiatrists define pseudohallucinations to mean hallucinations that patients actually recognize as
                    false perceptions, i.e. they have insight into the fact that they are hallucinating. The former
                    definition is probably more widely used.
                </ce:para>
                <ce:para id="p0230">According to which sense organ they appear to arise from, hallucinations are
                    classified as auditory, visual, olfactory, gustatory or somatic. Special forms of hallucinations
                    will also be discussed. See
                    <ce:cross-ref refid="f0010">Figure 9.1</ce:cross-ref>
                    <ce:float-anchor refid="f0010"/>
                    for an outline of the classification of hallucinations.
                </ce:para>
                <ce:section id="s0020">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0025">Auditory hallucinations</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0235">These are hallucinations of the hearing modality and are the most common type of
                        hallucinations in clinical psychiatry. Elementary hallucinations are simple, unstructured
                        sounds, e.g. whirring, buzzing, whistling or single words; this type of hallucination commonly
                        occurs in acute organic states. Complex hallucinations occur as spoken phrases, sentences or
                        even dialogue that are classified as:
                        <ce:list id="l0120">
                            <ce:list-item id="u0105">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0240">
                                    <ce:italic>Audible thoughts</ce:italic>
                                    (<ce:italic>first person</ce:italic>): patients hear their own thoughts spoken out
                                    loud as they think them. When patients experience their thoughts as echoed by a
                                    voice after they have thought them, it is termed thought echo.
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0110">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0245"><ce:italic>Second person auditory hallucinations</ce:italic>:
                                    patients hear a voice or voices talking directly to them. Second person
                                    hallucinations can be persecutory, highly critical, complimentary or issue commands
                                    to the patient (command hallucinations). Second person hallucinations are often
                                    associated with mood disorders with psychotic features and so will be critical or
                                    persecutory in a depressed patient or complimentary in a manic patient, i.e.
                                    mood-congruent hallucinations.
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0115">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0250"><ce:italic>Third person auditory hallucinations</ce:italic>:
                                    patients hear a voice or voices speaking about them, referring to them in the third
                                    person. This may take the form of two or more voices arguing or discussing the
                                    patient among themselves; or one or more voices giving a running commentary on the
                                    patient's thoughts or actions.
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                        </ce:list>
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0025">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0030">Visual hallucinations</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0255">These are hallucinations of the visual modality. They occur most commonly in
                        organic brain disturbances (delirium, occipital lobe tumours, epilepsy, dementia) and in the
                        context of psychoactive substance use (lysergic acid diethylamide (LSD), mescaline,
                        petrol/glue-sniffing, alcoholic hallucinosis). An autoscopic hallucination is the experience of
                        seeing an image of oneself in external space. The Charles Bonnet syndrome describes the
                        condition where patients experience complex visual hallucinations associated with no other
                        psychiatric symptoms or impairment in consciousness; it usually occurs in older adults and is
                        associated with loss of vision. Lilliputian hallucinations are hallucinations of miniature
                        people or animals.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0030">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0035">Somatic hallucinations</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0260">These are hallucinations of bodily sensation and include superficial, visceral
                        and kinaesthetic hallucinations.
                    </ce:para>
                    <ce:para id="p0265">
                        <ce:italic>Superficial hallucinations</ce:italic>
                        describe sensations on or just below the skin and may be:
                        <ce:list id="l0125">
                            <ce:list-item id="u0120">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0270">
                                    <ce:italic>Tactile</ce:italic>
                                    (<ce:italic>haptic</ce:italic>): experience of the skin being touched, pricked or
                                    pinched. Formication is the unpleasant sensation of insects crawling on or just
                                    below the skin; it is commonly associated with long-term cocaine use (cocaine bugs)
                                    and alcohol withdrawal.
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0125">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0275"><ce:italic>Thermal</ce:italic>: false perception of heat or cold.
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0130">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0280"><ce:italic>Hygric</ce:italic>: false perception of a fluid, e.g. ‘I
                                    can feel water sloshing in my brain’.
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0135">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0285">
                                    <ce:italic>Visceral</ce:italic>
                                    hallucinations describe false perceptions of the internal organs. Patients may be
                                    distressed by deep sensations of their organs throbbing, stretching, distending or
                                    vibrating.
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0140">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0290">
                                    <ce:italic>Kinaesthetic</ce:italic>
                                    hallucinations are false perceptions of joint or muscle sense. Patients may describe
                                    their limbs vibrating or being twisted. The fleeting but distressing sensation of
                                    free falling just as one is about to fall asleep is an example that most people have
                                    experienced (see hypnagogic hallucinations below).
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                        </ce:list>
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0035">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0040">Olfactory and gustatory hallucinations</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0295">These are the false perceptions of smell and taste. Note that they commonly
                        occur together because the two senses are closely related. Remember that in patients with
                        olfactory or gustatory hallucinations, it is important to rule out epilepsy (especially of the
                        temporal lobe) and other organic brain diseases.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0040">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0045">Special forms of hallucination</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0300">
                        <ce:italic>Hypnagogic hallucinations</ce:italic>
                        are false perceptions in any modality (usually auditory or visual) that occur as a person goes
                        to sleep; whereas, hypnopompic hallucinations occur as a person awakens. These occur in normal
                        people and are not indicative of psychopathology.
                    </ce:para>
                    <ce:para id="p0305">
                        <ce:italic>Extracampine hallucinations</ce:italic>
                        are false perceptions that occur outside the limits of a person's normal sensory field, e.g. a
                        patient describes hearing voices from 100 miles away. Patients often give delusional
                        explanations for this phenomenon.
                    </ce:para>
                    <ce:para id="p0310">
                        <ce:italic>A functional hallucination</ce:italic>
                        occurs when a normal sensory stimulus is required to precipitate a hallucination in that same
                        sensory modality, e.g. voices that are only heard when the doorbell rings. A reflex
                        hallucination occurs when a normal sensory stimulus in one modality precipitates a hallucination
                        in another, e.g. voices that are only heard whenever the lights are switched on.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
            </ce:section>
            <ce:section id="s0045">
                <ce:section-title id="st0050">Abnormal beliefs</ce:section-title>
                <ce:para id="p0315">Abnormal beliefs include primary and secondary delusions and overvalued ideas.
                </ce:para>
                <ce:section id="s0050">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0055">Delusions</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0320">A delusion is an unshakeable false belief that is not accepted by other members
                        of the patient's culture. It is important to understand the following characteristics of
                        delusional thinking:
                        <ce:list id="l0130">
                            <ce:list-item id="u0145">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0325">To the patient, there is no difference between a delusional belief
                                    and a true belief – they are the same experience. Therefore, only an external
                                    observer can diagnose a delusion. A delusion is to ideation what an hallucination is
                                    to perception.
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0150">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0330">The delusion is false because of faulty reasoning. A man's
                                    delusional belief that his wife is having an affair may actually be true (she may
                                    indeed be unfaithful), but it remains a delusion because the reason he gives for
                                    this belief is undoubtedly false. For example, she ‘must’ be having an affair
                                    because she is part of a top-secret sexual conspiracy to prove that he is a
                                    homosexual.
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0155">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0335">It is out of keeping with the patient's social and cultural
                                    background. It is crucial to establish that the belief is not one likely to be held
                                    by that person's subcultural group, e.g. a belief in the imminent second coming of
                                    Christ may be appropriate for a member of a religious group, but not for a formerly
                                    atheist, middle-aged businessman.
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                        </ce:list>
                        It is diagnostically significant to classify delusions as:
                        <ce:list id="l0135">
                            <ce:list-item id="u0160">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0345">Primary or secondary.</ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0165">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0350">Mood congruent or mood incongruent.</ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0170">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0355">Bizarre or non-bizarre.</ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0175">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0360">According to the content of the delusion.</ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                        </ce:list>
                    </ce:para>
                    <ce:para id="p0365">
                        <ce:italic>Primary delusions</ce:italic>
                        (autochthonous delusions) do not occur in response to any previous psychopathological state;
                        their genesis is un-understandable. They may be preceded by a delusional atmosphere (mood) where
                        patients have a sense that the world around them has been subtly altered, often in a sinister or
                        threatening way. In this state a fully formed delusion has not yet developed and patients appear
                        perplexed and apprehensive. Note that when a delusion occurs after a delusional atmosphere it is
                        still regarded as primary – the delusional atmosphere is probably a precursor to the fully
                        developed primary delusion. A delusional perception is also a primary delusion and occurs when a
                        delusional meaning is attached to a normal perception; e.g. a patient believed he was a
                        terrorist target because he heard an aeroplane flying in the distance. Primary delusions occur
                        typically in schizophrenia and other primary psychotic disorders. Secondary delusions are the
                        consequences of pre-existing psychopathological states, usually mood disorders (see
                        <ce:intra-ref id="ia9000" xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3863-2.00007-6#s0045">p. 51</ce:intra-ref>
                        and page<ce:intra-ref id="ia9005" xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3863-2.00008-8#s0070">
                        59</ce:intra-ref>). Many interrelated delusions that are centred on a common theme are termed
                        systematized delusions.
                    </ce:para>
                    <ce:para id="p0370">In mood-congruent delusions, the contents of the delusions are appropriate to
                        the patient's mood and are commonly seen in depression or mania with psychotic features.
                    </ce:para>
                    <ce:para id="p0375">Bizarre delusions are those which are completely impossible; e.g. the belief
                        that aliens have planted radioactive detonators in the patient's brain. They are considered to
                        be characteristic of schizophrenia.
                    </ce:para>
                    <ce:para id="p0380">
                        <ce:cross-ref refid="f0015">Figure 9.2</ce:cross-ref>
                        <ce:float-anchor refid="f0015"/>
                        lists the classification of delusions by their content. It is important that you are able to
                        label a delusion according to its content, so take some time to familiarize yourself with this
                        table.
                        <ce:display>
                            <ce:textbox role="alt0" id="b0015">
                                <ce:textbox-head>
                                    <ce:title>HINTS AND TIPS</ce:title>
                                </ce:textbox-head>
                                <ce:textbox-body>
                                    <ce:sections>
                                        <ce:para id="p0385">Note that the term ‘paranoid’ refers to any delusions or
                                            ideas that are unduly self-referent –typically delusions or ideas of
                                            persecution, grandeur or reference. It should not be used synonymously with
                                            the term persecutory; i.e. when a patient has a false belief that people are
                                            trying to harm him, do not say that he is paranoid, rather say that he has
                                            persecutory delusions.
                                        </ce:para>
                                    </ce:sections>
                                </ce:textbox-body>
                            </ce:textbox>
                        </ce:display>
                    </ce:para>
                    <ce:para id="p0390">Finally, beliefs that were previously held with delusional intensity but then
                        become held with less conviction are termed partial delusions. This occurs when patients start
                        recovering after receiving treatment.
                        <ce:display>
                            <ce:textbox role="alt1" id="b0020">
                                <ce:textbox-head>
                                    <ce:title>COMMUNICATION</ce:title>
                                </ce:textbox-head>
                                <ce:textbox-body>
                                    <ce:sections>
                                        <ce:para id="p0395">Direct questioning about perceptual experience may alienate
                                            a non-psychotic patient and raise undue suspicion in a psychotic patient. To
                                            maintain rapport with patients begin these questions with a primer such as:
                                            ‘I am now going to ask you some questions which may seem a little strange,
                                            but are routine questions which I ask all patients’.
                                        </ce:para>
                                    </ce:sections>
                                </ce:textbox-body>
                            </ce:textbox>
                        </ce:display>
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0055">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0060">Overvalued ideas</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0400">An overvalued idea is a plausible belief that a patient becomes preoccupied with
                        to an unreasonable extent. The key feature is that the pursuit of this idea causes considerable
                        distress to the patient or those living around them – it is overvalued. Patients who hold
                        overvalued ideas have usually had them for many years and typically have abnormalities of
                        personality. They are distinguished from delusions by the lack of a gross abnormality in
                        reasoning; these patients can often give fairly logical reasons for their beliefs. They differ
                        from obsessions in that they are not seen as recurrent intrusions. However, one will frequently
                        encounter beliefs that span definitions. Typical disorders that feature overvalued ideas are
                        anorexia nervosa, hypochondriacal disorder, dysmorphophobia, paranoid personality disorder and
                        morbid jealousy (this can also take the form of a delusion).
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
            </ce:section>
            <ce:section id="s0060">
                <ce:section-title id="st0065">Thought disorder</ce:section-title>
                <ce:para id="p0405">Describing the disturbance of a patient's thought form is one of the most
                    challenging tasks facing clinicians. This problem is compounded by two factors. Firstly, it is
                    impossible to know what patients are actually thinking – thought form has to be inferred from their
                    speech and behaviour. Secondly, the unfortunate situation has arisen where various authors in
                    psychiatry have described a different conceptual view of thought disorder, which has resulted in
                    conflicting and confusing classification systems. It is probably not that important that you are
                    able to classify and subgroup thought disorder, but rather that you have a clear understanding of
                    the individual definitions you intend to use and are able to recognize them in the patients that you
                    assess. In this regard, it is particularly helpful if you document and are able to cite examples of
                    the patient's speech in their own words.
                </ce:para>
                <ce:para id="p0410">Many patients with delusions are able to communicate in a clear and coherent manner;
                    although their beliefs may be false, their speech is organized. However, there is a subgroup of
                    psychotic patients who speak in such a disorganized way that it becomes difficult to understand what
                    they are saying. The coherency of patients with disorganized thinking varies from being mostly
                    understandable in patients exhibiting circumstantial thinking to being completely incomprehensible
                    in patients with a word salad phenomenon (see
                    <ce:cross-ref refid="f0020">Fig. 9.3</ce:cross-ref>
                    <ce:float-anchor refid="f0020"/>).
                </ce:para>
                <ce:para id="p0415">The following are important signs of disorganized thinking:</ce:para>
                <ce:section id="s0065">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0070">Circumstantial and tangential thinking</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0420">See page<ce:intra-ref id="ia9015"
                                                              xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3863-2.00008-8#s0070">
                        59</ce:intra-ref>.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0070">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0075">Flight of ideas</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0425">See page<ce:intra-ref id="ia9115"
                                                              xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3863-2.00008-8#s0070">
                        59</ce:intra-ref>.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0075">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0080">Loosening of association (derailment/knight's move thinking)
                    </ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0430">This is when the patient's train of thought shifts suddenly from one very
                        loosely or unrelated idea to the next. In its worst form, speech becomes a mixture of incoherent
                        words and phrases and is termed ‘word salad’. Loosening of association is characteristic of
                        schizophrenia. Note that some psychiatrists, but unfortunately not all, use the term formal
                        thought disorder synonymously with loosening of association.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0080">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0085">Thought blocking</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0435">This occurs when patients experience a sudden cessation to their flow of
                        thought, often in mid-sentence (observed as sudden breaks in speech). Patients have no recall of
                        what they were saying or thinking and thus continue talking about a different topic.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0085">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0090">Neologisms and idiosyncratic word use</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0440">Neologisms are new words created by the patient, often combining syllables of
                        other known words. Patients can also use recognized words idiosyncratically by attributing them
                        with a non-recognized meaning (metonyms).
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0090">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0095">Perseveration</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0445">This is when an initially correct response is inappropriately repeated, for
                        example, unnecessarily repeating a previously expressed word or phrase. Palilalia describes the
                        repetition of the last word of a sentence; logoclonia describes the repetition of the last
                        syllable of the last word. Perseveration is highly suggestive of organic brain disease.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0095">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0100">Echolalia</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0450">This is when patients senselessly repeat words or phrases spoken around them by
                        others – like a parrot.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0100">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0105">Irrelevant answers</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0455">Patients give answers that are completely unrelated to the original question.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
            </ce:section>
            <ce:section id="s0105">
                <ce:section-title id="st0110">Negative symptoms</ce:section-title>
                <ce:para id="p0460">Positive symptoms are those that are actively produced and include delusions,
                    hallucinations, loosening of association and bizarre speech or behaviour. This is opposed to
                    negative symptoms that indicate a clinical deficit and include marked apathy, poverty of thought and
                    speech, blunting of affect, social isolation, poor self-care and cognitive deficits. Patients can
                    have positive and negative symptoms simultaneously or, as often happens, develop a negative
                    presentation after initially presenting with predominantly positive symptoms. Remember that patients
                    with a depressed mood or those experiencing significant side-effects from psychotropic medication
                    may also present with negative symptoms.
                </ce:para>
            </ce:section>
            <ce:section id="s0110">
                <ce:section-title id="st0115">Psychomotor function</ce:section-title>
                <ce:para id="p0465">Although a relatively rare phenomenon in industrialized countries, some psychotic
                    patients will present with abnormalities of motor function. Motor system dysfunction in
                    schizophrenia is usually due to the extrapyramidal side-effects of neuroleptic medication (see
                    <ce:intra-ref xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3863-2.00002-7" id="ia0010">Ch. 2</ce:intra-ref>).
                    However, psychotic patients can occasionally present with impressive motor signs that are not caused
                    by psychiatric medication or a known organic brain disease. Although undoubtedly associated with the
                    patient's abnormal mental state, the cause of this psychomotor dysfunction is far from clarified.
                    The term ‘catatonia’ literally means extreme muscular tone or rigidity; however, it commonly
                    describes any excessive or decreased motor activity that is apparently purposeless and includes
                    abnormalities of movement, tone or position. Note that catatonic symptoms are not diagnostic of
                    schizophrenia; they may also be caused by brain diseases, metabolic abnormalities or psychoactive
                    substances, and can also occur in mood disorders.
                    <ce:cross-ref refid="f0025">Figure 9.4</ce:cross-ref>
                    <ce:float-anchor refid="f0025"/>
                    describes the common motor symptoms seen in schizophrenia.
                </ce:para>
            </ce:section>
        </ce:section>
        <ce:section id="s0115">
            <ce:section-title id="st0120">DIFFERENTIAL DIAGNOSIS</ce:section-title>
            <ce:para id="p0470">Psychotic symptoms are non-specific and are associated with many primary psychiatric
                illnesses. They can also present secondary to a general medical condition or psychoactive substance use.
                See
                <ce:cross-ref refid="f0030">Figure 9.5</ce:cross-ref>
                <ce:float-anchor refid="f0030"/>
                for the differential diagnosis for the psychotic patient.
            </ce:para>
            <ce:section id="s0120">
                <ce:section-title id="st0125">Psychotic disorders</ce:section-title>
                <ce:section id="s0125">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0130">Schizophrenia</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0475">There are no pathognomonic or singularly defining symptoms of schizophrenia; it
                        is a syndrome characterized by a heterogeneous cluster of symptoms and signs. The ICD-10 has set
                        out diagnostic guidelines based on the most commonly occurring symptom groups, which have been
                        discussed in the preceding section (
                        <ce:cross-ref refid="f0035">Fig. 9.6</ce:cross-ref>
                        <ce:float-anchor refid="f0035"/>). It is also important to establish that there has been a clear
                        and marked deterioration in the patient's social and work functioning.
                    </ce:para>
                    <ce:para id="p0480">In the past, psychiatrists used Schneider's first-rank symptoms to make the
                        diagnosis of schizophrenia. Kurt Schneider suggested that the presence of one or more first-rank
                        symptoms in the absence of organic disease was of pragmatic value in making the diagnosis of
                        schizophrenia. First-rank symptoms are still referred to so you should familiarize yourself with
                        them; they are presented in
                        <ce:cross-ref refid="f0040">Figure 9.7</ce:cross-ref>
                        <ce:float-anchor refid="f0040"/>.
                        <ce:display>
                            <ce:textbox role="alt0" id="b0025">
                                <ce:textbox-head>
                                    <ce:title>HINTS AND TIPS</ce:title>
                                </ce:textbox-head>
                                <ce:textbox-body>
                                    <ce:sections>
                                        <ce:para id="p0485">Memory aid: if you add ‘bizarre delusions’ and
                                            ‘hallucinations coming from a part of the body’ to Schneider's first-rank
                                            symptoms you will have the (a) to (d) criteria of the ICD-10 diagnostic
                                            guidelines for schizophrenia.
                                        </ce:para>
                                    </ce:sections>
                                </ce:textbox-body>
                            </ce:textbox>
                        </ce:display>
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0130">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0135">Schizophrenia subtypes</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0490">Due to the differing presentations of schizophrenia, researchers have tried to
                        identify schizophrenia subtypes. The importance of these subtypes is that they vary in their
                        prognosis and treatment response. The ICD-10 has coded the following subtypes, which are not
                        necessarily exclusive:
                        <ce:list id="l0140">
                            <ce:list-item id="u0180">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0495"><ce:italic>Paranoid schizophrenia</ce:italic>: dominated by the
                                    presence of delusions and hallucinations (positive symptoms). Negative and catatonic
                                    symptoms as well as thought disorganization are not prominent. The prognosis is
                                    usually better and the onset of illness later than the other subtypes.
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0185">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0500">
                                    <ce:italic>Hebephrenic</ce:italic>
                                    (<ce:italic>disorganized</ce:italic>)<ce:italic>schizophrenia</ce:italic>:
                                    characterized by thought disorganization, disturbed behaviour and inappropriate or
                                    flat affect. Delusions and hallucination are fleeting or not prominent. Onset of
                                    illness is earlier (15 to 25 years of age) and the prognosis poorer than paranoid
                                    schizophrenia.
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0190">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0505"><ce:italic>Catatonic schizophrenia</ce:italic>: a rare form
                                    characterized by one or more catatonic symptoms (see<ce:cross-ref refid="f0025">Fig.
                                        9.4</ce:cross-ref>).
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0195">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0510"><ce:italic>Residual schizophrenia</ce:italic>: 1 year of
                                    predominantly chronic negative symptoms which must have been preceded by at least
                                    one clear cut psychotic episode in the past.
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                        </ce:list>
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0135">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0140">Schizophrenia-like psychotic disorders</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0515">Some psychotic episodes with schizophrenia-like symptoms seem to have an abrupt
                        onset (without a prodromal phase), to be precipitated by an acute life stress or to have a
                        duration of symptoms less than that usually observed in schizophrenia. The ICD-10 codes these as
                        acute and transient psychotic disorders. The DSM-IV, on the other hand, suggests diagnoses of
                        schizophreniform disorder and brief psychotic disorder. Often these diagnoses are superseded by
                        a later diagnosis of schizophrenia as the clinical picture evolves.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0140">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0145">Schizoaffective disorder</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0520">Schizoaffective disorder describes the presentation of both schizophrenic and
                        mood (depressed or manic) symptoms that present in the same episode of illness, either
                        simultaneously or within a few days of each other. The mood symptoms should meet the criteria
                        for either a depressive or manic episode. Patients should also have at least one, preferably
                        two, of the typical schizophrenic symptoms – symptoms (a) to (d) as specified in the ICD-10
                        schizophrenia diagnostic guidelines (see<ce:cross-ref refid="f0035">Fig. 9.6</ce:cross-ref>).
                        Depending on the particular mood symptoms displayed, this disorder can be coded in the ICD-10 as
                        schizoaffective disorder, manic type or schizoaffective disorder, depressed type.
                        <ce:display>
                            <ce:textbox role="alt0" id="b0030">
                                <ce:textbox-head>
                                    <ce:title>HINTS AND TIPS</ce:title>
                                </ce:textbox-head>
                                <ce:textbox-body>
                                    <ce:sections>
                                        <ce:para id="p0525">When psychiatrists talk about the typical symptoms of
                                            schizophrenia, they are generally referring to (a) to (d) of the ICD-10
                                            criteria for schizophrenia (or Schneider's first-rank symptoms), e.g.
                                            delusions of control, running commentary hallucinations, etc.
                                        </ce:para>
                                    </ce:sections>
                                </ce:textbox-body>
                            </ce:textbox>
                        </ce:display>
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0145">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0150">Delusional disorder</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0530">In this disorder, the development of a single or set of delusions for the period
                        of at least 3 months is the most prominent or only symptom. It usually has its onset in middle
                        age and expressed delusions may persist throughout the patient's life and include persecutory,
                        grandiose and hypochondriacal delusions. Typically schizophrenic delusions, such as delusions of
                        thought control or passivity, exclude this diagnosis. Hallucinations, if present, tend to be
                        only fleeting and are not typically schizophrenic in nature; brief depressive symptoms may also
                        be evident. Affect, speech and behaviour are all normal and these patients usually have
                        well-preserved personal and social skills. Rarely, patients may present with an induced
                        delusional disorder (<ce:italic>folie à deux</ce:italic>), which occurs when a non-psychotic
                        patient with close emotional ties to another person suffering from delusions (usually a dominant
                        figure) begins to share those delusional ideas themselves. The delusions in the non-psychotic
                        patient tend to resolve when the two are separated.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
            </ce:section>
            <ce:section id="s0150">
                <ce:section-title id="st0155">Mood (affective) disorders</ce:section-title>
                <ce:section id="s0155">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0160">Manic episode with psychotic features</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0535">See<ce:intra-ref xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3863-2.00008-8" id="ia0015">Chapter
                        8</ce:intra-ref>.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0160">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0165">Depressive episode, severe with psychotic features</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0540">See<ce:intra-ref xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3863-2.00007-6" id="ia0020">Chapter
                        7</ce:intra-ref>.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
            </ce:section>
            <ce:section id="s0165">
                <ce:section-title id="st0170">Psychotic episodes secondary to a general medical condition or
                    psychoactive substance use
                </ce:section-title>
                <ce:para id="p0545">A medical or psychoactive substance cause of psychosis should always be sought for
                    and ruled out.
                    <ce:cross-ref refid="f0045">Figure 9.8</ce:cross-ref>
                    <ce:float-anchor refid="f0045"/>
                    lists the medical and substance-related causes of psychotic episodes. The medical condition or
                    substance use should predate the development of the psychosis and symptoms should resolve with
                    treatment of the condition or abstinence from the offending substance. Absence of previous psychotic
                    episodes and absence of a family history of schizophrenia also supports this diagnosis.
                </ce:para>
            </ce:section>
            <ce:section id="s0170">
                <ce:section-title id="st0175">Delirium and dementia</ce:section-title>
                <ce:para id="p0550">Visual hallucinations and delusions are common in delirium and may also occur in
                    dementia, particularly diffuse Lewy body dementia (see<ce:intra-ref
                            xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3863-2.00014-3" id="ia0025">Ch. 14</ce:intra-ref>).
                </ce:para>
            </ce:section>
            <ce:section id="s0175">
                <ce:section-title id="st0180">Personality disorder</ce:section-title>
                <ce:para id="p0555">In general, schizophrenia presents with a clear change in behaviour and functioning,
                    sometimes with a prodrome, whereas patients with a personality or neurodevelopmental disorder have
                    never achieved a normal baseline. Schizotypal (personality) disorder is characterized by eccentric
                    behaviour and peculiarities of thinking and appearance. Although there are no clear psychotic
                    symptoms evident and its course resembles that of a personality disorder, the ICD-10 actually
                    describes schizotypal disorder in the chapter on psychotic disorders. This is because it is more
                    prevalent among relatives of patients with schizophrenia and, occasionally, it progresses to overt
                    schizophrenia. Borderline, paranoid and schizoid personality disorders also share similar features
                    to schizophrenia without displaying clear-cut psychotic symptoms. Personality disorders are
                    discussed in greater detail in<ce:intra-ref xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3863-2.00016-7" id="ia0030">
                        Chapter 16</ce:intra-ref>.
                </ce:para>
            </ce:section>
            <ce:section id="s0180">
                <ce:section-title id="st0185">Neurodevelopmental disorder</ce:section-title>
                <ce:para id="p0560">Social difficulties and rigid thinking are found in both autistic spectrum disorders
                    and schizophrenia. See<ce:intra-ref xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3863-2.00027-1" id="ia0035">Chapter
                        27</ce:intra-ref>.
                </ce:para>
            </ce:section>
        </ce:section>
        <ce:section id="s0185">
            <ce:section-title id="st0190">ALGORITHM FOR THE DIAGNOSIS OF PSYCHOTIC DISORDERS</ce:section-title>
            <ce:para id="p0565">See
                <ce:cross-ref refid="f0050">Figure 9.9</ce:cross-ref>
                <ce:float-anchor refid="f0050"/>.
            </ce:para>
        </ce:section>
        <ce:section id="s0190">
            <ce:section-title id="st0195">ASSESSMENT</ce:section-title>
            <ce:section id="s0195">
                <ce:section-title id="st0200">History</ce:section-title>
                <ce:para id="p0570">The following questions may be helpful in eliciting psychotic phenomena on mental
                    state examination:
                </ce:para>
                <ce:section id="s0200">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0205">Hallucinations</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0575">
                        <ce:list id="l0145">
                            <ce:list-item id="u0200">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0580">Do you ever hear strange noises or voices when there is no one else
                                    about?
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0205">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0585">Do you ever hear your own thoughts spoken aloud such that someone
                                    standing next to you might possibly hear them? (audible thoughts – first person
                                    auditory hallucinations)
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0210">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0590">Do you ever hear your thoughts echoed just after you have thought
                                    them? (thought echo)
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0215">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0595">Do these voices talk directly to you or give you commands? (second
                                    person auditory hallucinations)
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0220">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0600">Do these voices ever talk about you with each other or make comments
                                    about what you are doing? (third person auditory hallucinations/running commentary)
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                        </ce:list>
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0205">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0210">Delusions</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0605">
                        <ce:list id="l0150">
                            <ce:list-item id="u0225">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0610">Are you afraid that someone is trying to harm or poison you?
                                    (persecutory delusions)
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0230">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0615">Have you noticed that people are doing or saying things that have a
                                    special meaning for you? (delusions of reference)
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0235">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0620">Do you have any special abilities or powers? (grandiose delusions)
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0240">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0625">Does it seem as though you are being controlled or influenced by
                                    some external force? (delusions of control)
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0245">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0630">Are thoughts that don't belong to you being put into your head?
                                    (thought insertion)
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                        </ce:list>
                    </ce:para>
                    <ce:para id="p0635">It is important to obtain collateral information from the patient's GP, family
                        and care coordinator (if they have one) to establish premorbid personality and functioning as
                        well as pattern of deterioration.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
            </ce:section>
            <ce:section id="s0210">
                <ce:section-title id="st0215">Examination</ce:section-title>
                <ce:para id="p0640">A basic physical examination including a thorough neurological and endocrine system
                    examination should be performed on all patients with psychotic symptoms.
                </ce:para>
            </ce:section>
            <ce:section id="s0215">
                <ce:section-title id="st0220">Investigations</ce:section-title>
                <ce:para id="p0645">
                    <ce:list id="l0155">
                        <ce:list-item id="u0250">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0650">Blood investigations are performed to:
                                <ce:list id="l8000">
                                    <ce:list-item id="u0255">
                                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                        <ce:para id="p0655">Exclude possible medical or substance-related causes of
                                            psychosis
                                        </ce:para>
                                    </ce:list-item>
                                    <ce:list-item id="u0260">
                                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                        <ce:para id="p0660">Establish baseline values before administering
                                            antipsychotics and other psychotropic drugs that may alter blood composition
                                        </ce:para>
                                    </ce:list-item>
                                    <ce:list-item id="u0265">
                                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                        <ce:para id="p0665">Assess renal and liver functioning which may affect
                                            elimination of drugs that are likely to be taken long-term and possibly in
                                            depot form.
                                        </ce:para>
                                    </ce:list-item>
                                </ce:list>
                            </ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                        <ce:list-item id="u0270">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0670">If the patient presents with a first episode of psychosis, a good basic
                                screen comprises full blood count, erythrocyte sedimentation rate, urea and
                                electrolytes, thyroid function, liver function tests, glucose, serum calcium, and a
                                syphilis serology test if syphilis is suspected.
                            </ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                        <ce:list-item id="u0275">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0675">A urine drug screen should always be done because illicit drugs both
                                cause and exacerbate a psychosis.
                            </ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                        <ce:list-item id="u0280">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0680">An electrocardiogram (ECG) should be done in patients with cardiac
                                problems as many antipsychotics prolong the QT interval and have the potential to cause
                                lethal ventricular arrhythmia.
                            </ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                        <ce:list-item id="u0285">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0685">The use of a routine EEG or CT scan to help exclude an organic psychosis
                                (e.g. temporal lobe epilepsy, brain tumour) varies between psychiatric units; they
                                should always be considered in atypical cases, cases with treatment resistance, or if
                                there are cognitive or neurological abnormalities.
                            </ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                    </ce:list>
                </ce:para>
            </ce:section>
        </ce:section>
        <ce:section id="s0220">
            <ce:section-title id="st0225">DISCUSSION OF CASE STUDY</ce:section-title>
            <ce:para id="p0690">Mr PP meets the ICD-10 criteria for schizophrenia, paranoid subtype. He has had a marked
                deterioration in his social and work functioning. He has delusions of persecution (believing he was a
                victim of government experiments), thought control (believing that ideas were being planted in his head
                (thought insertion)) and reference (believing that the man in pub was referring specifically to him).
                His claim that he knew these things after hearing the neighbour's dog bark suggests delusional
                perception. He also has second person command hallucinations and third person, running commentary
                hallucinations. ‘Receiving coded information’ from the radio might be a hallucination or a delusion of
                reference depending on how Mr PP described this experience subjectively. Mr PP's description that ‘all
                was not right’ could indicate the presence of a delusional atmosphere, prior to the development of the
                full-blown delusions.
            </ce:para>
            <ce:para id="p0695">It is imperative that a substance-induced psychotic disorder or psychotic disorder
                secondary to a medical condition is excluded. It would be important to ascertain the duration of Mr PP's
                psychotic symptoms. It seems as though he has had schizophrenic symptoms for over a month. If the
                duration of symptoms had been less than a month, it would be advisable to diagnose a schizophrenia-like
                psychotic disorder, e.g. acute and transient psychotic disorder. It is important to rule out a mood
                disorder with psychotic features. The presence of a mood episode associated with simultaneous
                schizophrenic symptoms would suggest a schizoaffective episode. Prominent hallucinations militate
                against a diagnosis of delusional disorder.
            </ce:para>
            <ce:para id="p0700">Now go on to
                <ce:intra-ref xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3863-2.00019-2" id="ia0040">Chapter 19</ce:intra-ref>
                to read more about the psychotic disorders and their management.
            </ce:para>
        </ce:section>
    </ce:sections>
</chapter>