<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter id="c0005" version="5.3" docsubtype="chp" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.elsevier.com/xml/bk/dtd"
         xmlns:ce="http://www.elsevier.com/xml/common/dtd" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <info>
        <ce:pii>B978-0-7234-3864-9.00001-0</ce:pii>
        <ce:doi>10.1016/B978-0-7234-3864-9.00001-0</ce:doi>
        <ce:isbn>978-0-7234-3864-9</ce:isbn>
        <ce:copyright type="full-transfer" year="2015">Elsevier Ltd</ce:copyright>
    </info>
    <ce:floats>
        <ce:figure id="f0010">
            <ce:label>Fig. 1.1</ce:label>
            <ce:caption id="ca0010">
                <ce:simple-para id="sp0010">Units of alcohol. These refer to a standard pub measure of wine (12% alcohol
                    by volume), a small pub measure of spirits (40% alcohol by volume) and standard strength beer (3–4%
                    alcohol by volume). An easy way to work out the units for a drink is to remember that the alcohol
                    percentage is equivalent to the number of units in one litre of the drink (e.g. a litre of 40%
                    whiskey contains 40 units and a 330-mL bottle of 6% lager contains 2 units).
                </ce:simple-para>
            </ce:caption>
            <ce:link locator="f01-01-9780723436331" id="lk0010"/>
        </ce:figure>
        <ce:figure id="f0015">
            <ce:label>Fig. 1.2</ce:label>
            <ce:caption id="ca0015">
                <ce:simple-para id="sp0015">Causes of pruritus.</ce:simple-para>
            </ce:caption>
            <ce:link locator="f01-02-9780723436331" id="lk0015"/>
        </ce:figure>
        <ce:figure id="f0020">
            <ce:label>Fig. 1.3</ce:label>
            <ce:caption id="ca0020">
                <ce:simple-para id="sp0020">Causes of dysphagia.</ce:simple-para>
            </ce:caption>
            <ce:link locator="f01-03-9780723436331" id="lk0020"/>
        </ce:figure>
        <ce:figure id="f0025">
            <ce:label>Fig. 1.4</ce:label>
            <ce:caption id="ca0025">
                <ce:simple-para id="sp0025">Causes of rectal bleeding.</ce:simple-para>
            </ce:caption>
            <ce:link locator="f01-04-9780723436331" id="lk0025"/>
        </ce:figure>
        <ce:figure id="f0030">
            <ce:label>Fig. 1.5</ce:label>
            <ce:caption id="ca0030">
                <ce:simple-para id="sp0030">Causes and features of abnormalities of speech arising from lesions at
                    specific anatomical sites.
                </ce:simple-para>
            </ce:caption>
            <ce:link locator="f01-05-9780723436331" id="lk0030"/>
        </ce:figure>
        <ce:figure id="f0035">
            <ce:label>Fig. 1.6</ce:label>
            <ce:caption id="ca0035">
                <ce:simple-para id="sp0035">Differences in the history between hyperthyroidism and hypothyroidism.
                </ce:simple-para>
            </ce:caption>
            <ce:link locator="f01-06-9780723436331" id="lk0035"/>
        </ce:figure>
        <ce:figure id="f0040">
            <ce:label>Fig. 1.7</ce:label>
            <ce:caption id="ca0040">
                <ce:simple-para id="sp0040">Symptoms of diabetes mellitus.</ce:simple-para>
            </ce:caption>
            <ce:link locator="f01-07-9780723436331" id="lk0040"/>
        </ce:figure>
        <ce:figure id="f0045">
            <ce:label>Fig. 1.8</ce:label>
            <ce:caption id="ca0045">
                <ce:simple-para id="sp0045">Causes of bone pain.</ce:simple-para>
            </ce:caption>
            <ce:link locator="f01-08-9780723436331" id="lk0045"/>
        </ce:figure>
    </ce:floats>
    <ce:label>1</ce:label>
    <ce:title>Taking a history</ce:title>
    <objectives>
        <ce:section-title id="st0010">Objectives</ce:section-title>
        <ce:para id="p0010">The key learning points for this chapter:
            <ce:list id="l0010">
                <ce:list-item id="u0010">
                    <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                    <ce:para id="p0015">Take a history from a patient.</ce:para>
                </ce:list-item>
                <ce:list-item id="u0015">
                    <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                    <ce:para id="p0020">Use open questions initially, followed by more specific questions based on your
                        developing differential diagnosis.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:list-item>
                <ce:list-item id="u0020">
                    <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                    <ce:para id="p0025">Ask relevant questions for each organ system.</ce:para>
                </ce:list-item>
            </ce:list>
        </ce:para>
    </objectives>
    <ce:sections>
        <ce:section id="s0010">
            <ce:section-title id="st0015">GENERAL PRINCIPLES: THE BEDSIDE MANNER</ce:section-title>
            <ce:para id="p0030">Medical students are often told that ‘90% of the diagnosis is in the history’. Although
                there is a large amount of truth in this statement, this is only the case if your history-taking skills
                are accurate and relevant. This, in turn, is largely dependent on your bedside manner and the ability to
                build up a good rapport with your patient. There is no easy recipe for developing a good bedside manner
                but courtesy, patience and letting the patient express their ideas, concerns and expectations are
                essential ingredients. The mnemonic ‘PEAS’ (Pause, Empathize, Acknowledge, Summarize) can be used to
                remember the basis of good communication.
            </ce:para>
            <ce:para id="p0035">Whenever you meet a patient, introduce yourself politely and do not forget relatives or
                friends who may also be present. Try to put the patient at ease, as visiting the doctor is very
                stressful for most people, particularly if they think that they have a serious illness. If you cannot
                speak the same language, try to get an interpreter. If a patient has hearing difficulties, sit closer,
                write things down or speak louder!
            </ce:para>
            <ce:para id="p0040">The aims of the history are as follows:
                <ce:list id="l0015">
                    <ce:list-item id="u0025">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0045">To establish rapport with the patient.</ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0030">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0050">To obtain an accurate, sequential account of the patient's symptoms through
                            open questions and create a differential diagnosis.
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0035">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0055">To ask specific questions to focus on the most likely diagnoses.</ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0040">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0060">To determine risk factors for these possible diagnoses.</ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0045">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0065">To put this problem or problems into the context of the patient's life.
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                </ce:list>
            </ce:para>
            <ce:para id="p0070">This chapter provides a framework for taking a comprehensive history. However, the
                important thing is that you develop an approach with which you are comfortable and then practise it
                again and again. In this way you will not miss things out and you will be able to concentrate more on
                what the patient is telling you rather than what comes next. With experience you will recognize patterns
                and explore different avenues in the history.
            </ce:para>
            <ce:para id="p0075">Make sure not to miss out on non-verbal clues, as facial expression and body posture can
                sometimes tell you more than the words themselves. If you are looking up, they will also feel that you
                are genuinely listening to what they are saying. It is important to strike a good balance between
                recording the history accurately and maintaining eye contact.
            </ce:para>
            <ce:para id="p0080">As a general principle, start the consultation by asking very open-ended questions, such
                as ‘How are you?’ or ‘What symptoms have made you come to the clinic today?’ This gives the patient the
                opportunity to say what they want. Then ask more specific questions to clarify important aspects.
            </ce:para>
            <ce:para id="p0085">Try to take the history and then write it down afterwards; it enables you to listen and
                appear to be listening without distraction, plus you can organize your thoughts before committing them
                to paper. However, when you are learning it may be easier to make notes as you go along; you can also
                have prompts on your paper to enable you to fill in all sections. As you gain experience, you will find
                it easier to memorize the patient's history and write it down later.
            </ce:para>
        </ce:section>
        <ce:section id="s0015">
            <ce:section-title id="st0020">THE HISTORY</ce:section-title>
            <ce:para id="p0090">At the start of every history you should always:
                <ce:list id="l0020">
                    <ce:list-item id="u0050">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0095">Document the date, time and place of consultation. This should be done on
                            both sides and each subsequent sheet of paper. (Remember that the clerking is a legal
                            document.)
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0055">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0100">Record the age, sex and occupation of the patient.</ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0060">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0105">Document who referred the patient and if they were seen as an emergency.
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0065">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0110">Document your name, grade and role (e.g. CT1 van Boxel, Gen Surg SHO on
                            call)
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                </ce:list>
            </ce:para>
        </ce:section>
        <ce:section id="s0020">
            <ce:section-title id="st0025">PRESENTING COMPLAINT (PC)</ce:section-title>
            <ce:para id="p0115">This is a sentence or short list explaining the reason the patient has seen you today.
                Resist the temptation to write the entire history in this section, particularly when there are multiple
                symptoms; however, mentioning an obvious background condition can be helpful (e.g. ‘One week increasing
                shortness of breath and productive cough. Background: 10-year history of COPD’).
            </ce:para>
        </ce:section>
        <ce:section id="s0025">
            <ce:section-title id="st0030">HISTORY OF THE PRESENTING COMPLAINT (HPC)</ce:section-title>
            <ce:para id="p0120">This is where the presenting complaint is explored in great detail. It is impossible to
                describe a system that will work for all complaints in every situation. You will need to develop your
                own techniques, likes and dislikes. Inadequate relevant detail in this section is the commonest problem
                in medical student histories:
                <ce:list id="l0025">
                    <ce:list-item id="u0070">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0125">Aim to obtain a coherent, sequential chronological description of the events
                            leading to the consultation.
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0075">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0130">Ask the relevant questions to the symptoms (e.g. for pain, ‘Where is it?’,
                            ‘What is its character?’)
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0080">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0135">Keep the differential diagnoses for a symptom in your mind and seek evidence
                            to confirm or refute them.
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0085">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0140">Use the review of symptoms questions for the system you suspect to fill in
                            extra detail (e.g. if the complaint is a cough, ask about dyspnoea, pain, sputum, etc., and
                            record it in the presenting complaint).
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0090">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0145">Ask about the relevant risk factors (e.g. if pulmonary embolus is suspected
                            ask about immobility, travel, etc.).
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0095">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0150">Recapitulate the history back to the patient, as this helps cement the story
                            in your mind and reassures the patient that you are listening.
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0100">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0155">If the history is long, or vague, using the opening question ‘So when did
                            you last feel well?’ gives a platform to begin from.
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0105">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0160">Seek collateral history from witnesses, friends or family where necessary
                            (e.g. after a seizure). It is always worth asking the patient first whether they mind you
                            speaking to family or friends.
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0110">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0165">With chronic complaints, it is vital to ask about how the symptoms are
                            affecting the patient's life.
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0115">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0170">Document relevant negative findings (e.g. headache, but no photophobia or
                            neck stiffness).
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                </ce:list>
            </ce:para>
            <ce:para id="p0175">Finally, ask if they have any thoughts or worries as to what the diagnosis might be;
                this can be very enlightening and will help you build a good working relationship as you will be
                addressing their concerns. What the doctor is interested in and what the patient is interested in can be
                diametrically different.
                <ce:display>
                    <ce:textbox role="alt0" id="b0010">
                        <ce:textbox-head>
                            <ce:title>HINTS AND TIPS</ce:title>
                        </ce:textbox-head>
                        <ce:textbox-body>
                            <ce:sections>
                                <ce:para id="p0180">If the patient presents with pain, the SOCRATES principle is a
                                    useful framework for remembering to ask all the relevant information: Site, Onset,
                                    Character, Radiation, Associated features, Timing, Exacerbating/relieving factors,
                                    Severity.
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:sections>
                        </ce:textbox-body>
                    </ce:textbox>
                </ce:display>
            </ce:para>
        </ce:section>
        <ce:section id="s0030">
            <ce:section-title id="st0035">PAST MEDICAL HISTORY</ce:section-title>
            <ce:para id="p0185">Ask the patient if they have had any previous operations or medical problems. It is
                prudent to probe a little about each illness and how the diagnosis was made. Lists of past history are
                commonly and sometimes wrongly carried forward from one hospital visit to the next. Record the history
                in chronological order and, where possible, record the year, hospital and consultant involved for each
                episode. Many patients may forget past illnesses, particularly if anxious, and it is worth developing a
                routine to ask them specifically about diabetes, hypertension, angina or heart disease, rheumatic fever,
                tuberculosis, epilepsy, asthma/emphysema/bronchitis, jaundice, stroke or transient ischaemic attacks.
                <ce:display>
                    <ce:textbox role="alt0" id="b0015">
                        <ce:textbox-head>
                            <ce:title>HINTS AND TIPS</ce:title>
                        </ce:textbox-head>
                        <ce:textbox-body>
                            <ce:sections>
                                <ce:para id="p0190">MJTHREADS is a useful mnemonic for remembering to ask about specific
                                    medical conditions: Myocardial infarction, Jaundice, Tuberculosis, Hypertension,
                                    Rheumatic fever, Epilepsy, Asthma, Diabetes, Stroke.
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:sections>
                        </ce:textbox-body>
                    </ce:textbox>
                </ce:display>
            </ce:para>
        </ce:section>
        <ce:section id="s0035">
            <ce:section-title id="st0040">MEDICATIONS AND ALLERGIES (DHX)</ce:section-title>
            <ce:para id="p0195">Record which medications the patient is currently taking, how often and at what dose. If
                the prescribed medications are not being taken, ask why. Ask if there have been any recent changes in
                medication. Always ask what drugs the patient has taken in the past. For example, a patient with
                pulmonary fibrosis as a consequence of amiodarone may well have stopped taking it years before! Finally,
                ask about any non-prescription medications that may be obtained from a chemist or health food shop.
            </ce:para>
            <ce:para id="p0200">Does the patient have any allergies to any medications or anything else at all, no
                matter how trivial? If yes, what was the exact nature of the reaction? Was it anaphylaxis or did they
                experience a rash? It is worth asking about penicillin directly as many patients state they have a
                penicillin allergy but on closer questioning, they may describe a non-specific symptom and a beta-lactam
                antibiotic can be given safely if the need is there.
            </ce:para>
            <ce:para id="p0205">If the patient says they have no allergies it is traditional to write ‘No known drug
                allergies’ (NKDA).
            </ce:para>
        </ce:section>
        <ce:section id="s0040">
            <ce:section-title id="st0045">FAMILY HISTORY (FHX)</ce:section-title>
            <ce:para id="p0210">Do any diseases ‘run’ in the patient's family – in particular ischaemic heart disease,
                cancer, diabetes and autoimmune disorders? Record illnesses in close relatives, including age of death
                where relevant. Generally speaking, family members affected before the age of 60 are deemed to be
                relevant. Drawing a family tree can be helpful in some patients.
            </ce:para>
        </ce:section>
        <ce:section id="s0045">
            <ce:section-title id="st0050">SOCIAL HISTORY (SHX)</ce:section-title>
            <ce:para id="p0215">The importance of this part of the history is to establish how the illness affects the
                patient's life and how they are coping at home. Ask about:
                <ce:list id="l0030">
                    <ce:list-item id="u0120">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0220">Who is at home? If they have a partner, are they fit and well?</ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0125">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0225">What is the home like? If the patient is elderly, is there a warden?
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0130">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0230">If the patient is disabled, have appropriate modifications been made?
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0135">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0235">Do they need help with daily tasks, such as washing, dressing, feeding,
                            cleaning or shopping?
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0140">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0240">Do they have dependent children? Who is looking after them at the moment?
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0145">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0245">Is there a nearby relative who helps or does the patient have
                            meals-on-wheels, a home help or a district nurse?
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0150">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0250">What is their occupation? Details of their past and present occupation can
                            be important (e.g. industrial lung disease).
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0155">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0255">Are they still able to work despite the current problem?</ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0160">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0260">Some diagnoses can be particularly important in relation to work, such as
                            heavy goods vehicle drivers and epilepsy.
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0165">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0265">Do they, or did they, smoke? Smoking is a significant cause of many
                            diseases. Record smoking in pack/years
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0170">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0270">Alcohol past and present. Record as units per week (
                            <ce:cross-ref refid="f0010">Fig. 1.1</ce:cross-ref>
                            <ce:float-anchor refid="f0010"/>).
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0175">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0275">Do they use ‘recreational’ drugs? These have health, social and financial
                            implications.
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0180">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0280">Have they recently been abroad? They may have been exposed to different
                            infective agents.
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0185">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0285">Do they have pets (particularly budgerigars, pigeons and parrots)?</ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                    <ce:list-item id="u0190">
                        <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                        <ce:para id="p0290">Sexual history is not appropriate in every history but may be important
                            (e.g. for hepatitis or human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)).
                        </ce:para>
                    </ce:list-item>
                </ce:list>
            </ce:para>
        </ce:section>
        <ce:section id="s0050">
            <ce:section-title id="st0055">SYSTEMS REVIEW</ce:section-title>
            <ce:para id="p0295">Patients occasionally focus on one minor symptom while omitting to tell you of another
                more significant symptom. In fact, this can be a deliberate act, asking the doctor to deal with a simple
                problem (e.g. sore throat) while deciding whether to ask for help with the real worry such as impotence
                or rectal bleeding. Performing a quick systems review will prevent you from missing other important
                diseases.
            </ce:para>
            <ce:para id="p0300">Alternatively, if the symptoms are multiple and non-specific, a review of systems can
                shine light on the consultation and aid a differential diagnosis.
            </ce:para>
            <ce:para id="p0305">The symptoms to ask about in each system are outlined below. This list cannot be
                exhaustive and some symptoms are repeated as they cross organ systems though with different emphasis.
            </ce:para>
            <ce:section id="s0055">
                <ce:section-title id="st0060">General symptoms</ce:section-title>
                <ce:section id="s0060">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0065">Fatigue</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0310">This is a non-specific symptom that can accompany many organic as well as
                        psychiatric diseases. Look particularly for evidence of anaemia or hypothyroidism.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0065">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0070">Appetite</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0315">Anorexia is a feature of many diseases, again organic and psychiatric; increased
                        appetite despite weight loss is seen in hyperthyroidism. Distinguish between reduced appetite,
                        nausea or dysphagia
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0070">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0075">Weight change</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0320">Weight loss can be deliberate (dieting) or due to chronic disease. The causes
                        are discussed in detail in<ce:intra-ref xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00012-5" id="ia0010">
                            Ch. 12</ce:intra-ref>.
                    </ce:para>
                    <ce:para id="p0325">Weight gain is seen in pregnancy, hypothyroidism, Cushing's syndrome, polycystic
                        ovarian disease and ‘comfort eating’ due to anxiety or depression.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0075">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0080">Sweats</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0330">Drenching sweats occurring at night are seen in lymphoma, chronic leukaemia and
                        tuberculosis. This is commonly referred to as B-symptoms (and addition to weight loss and
                        fever).
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0080">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0085">Pruritus (itching)</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0335">Pruritus can be due to local skin disease or systemic disease, as shown in
                        <ce:cross-ref refid="f0015">Fig. 1.2</ce:cross-ref>
                        <ce:float-anchor refid="f0015"/>.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0085">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0090">Sleep pattern</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0340">If there is difficulty in sleeping, ask if the problem is in going to sleep or
                        in waking early. Difficulty in getting off to sleep is often due to worry or anxiety, whereas
                        early morning wakening is a feature of depression. Sleep apnoea is common and can be
                        debilitating as hypersomnolence limits daytime function. The commonest medical condition
                        affecting sleep is obstructive sleep apnoea (see<ce:intra-ref
                                xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00030-7" id="ia0015">Ch. 30</ce:intra-ref>). Ask
                        about snoring, whether sleep is refreshing, morning headaches and restless leg movements. The
                        patient's partner is often the best source of information.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
            </ce:section>
            <ce:section id="s0090">
                <ce:section-title id="st0095">Cardiovascular symptoms</ce:section-title>
                <ce:section id="s0095">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0100">Chest pain</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0345">Establish the site, radiation, character, exacerbating and relieving factors,
                        and severity; discussed in detail in<ce:intra-ref xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00004-6"
                                                                          id="ia0020">Ch. 4</ce:intra-ref>.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0100">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0105">Shortness of breath (dyspnoea) and exercise tolerance
                    </ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0350">Exertional dyspnoea can be due to poor left ventricular function, pulmonary
                        oedema, arrhythmia or valvular disease (see<ce:intra-ref
                                xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00030-7" id="ia0025">Ch. 30</ce:intra-ref>).
                    </ce:para>
                    <ce:para id="p0355">Orthopnoea is breathlessness on lying flat, usually from increased pulmonary
                        venous congestion. This symptom can be present in diaphragm palsy and even in chronic
                        obstructive pulmonary disease, as diaphragmatic input to ventilation is less efficient when the
                        patient is lying flat.
                    </ce:para>
                    <ce:para id="p0360">Paroxysmal nocturnal dyspnoea (PND) is waking during the night due to severe
                        breathlessness (pulmonary oedema).
                    </ce:para>
                    <ce:para id="p0365">Sudden onset of breathlessness, irrespective of body position or exercise, is
                        often due to arrhythmia, pneumothorax or pulmonary embolism (see<ce:intra-ref
                                xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00005-8" id="ia0030">Ch. 5</ce:intra-ref>).
                    </ce:para>
                    <ce:para id="p0370">Taking a relevant exercise tolerance history is important. Ask the patient
                        whether they can walk up a set of stairs (in one go, without being out of breath once upstairs)
                        and how far they can walk on the flat. Remember that joint problems may be the limiting factor
                        rather than cardiorespiratory reserve.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0105">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0110">Blackouts (syncope)</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0375">Syncope is the transient loss of consciousness and motor tone, which may be due
                        to arrhythmia, valvular heart disease, postural hypotension or vertebrobasilar insufficiency
                        (see<ce:intra-ref xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00022-8" id="ia0035">Ch. 22</ce:intra-ref>
                        ).
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0110">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0115">Palpitations</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0380">Palpitations mean different things to different people and they should be
                        explored carefully as they may be insignificant or they may be life-threatening. Most commonly
                        they refer to awareness of one's heart beating (see<ce:intra-ref
                                xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00006-X" id="ia0040">Ch. 6</ce:intra-ref>).
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0115">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0120">Ankle and calf swelling</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0385">This can be due to right ventricular failure, low plasma oncotic pressure (e.g.
                        decreased albumin levels) or drugs (e.g. calcium channel blockers), or it can be gravitational.
                    </ce:para>
                    <ce:para id="p0390">Calf swelling can be due to:
                        <ce:list id="l0035">
                            <ce:list-item id="u0195">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0395">Deep vein thrombosis: recent travel, immobility or surgery,
                                    pregnancy, combined oral contraceptive pill, family history, malignancy.
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0200">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0400">Ruptured Baker's cyst: in the elderly, secondary to osteoarthritis
                                    of the knee.
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0205">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0405">Muscle trauma.</ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0210">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0410">Cellulitis.</ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0215">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0415">Tumour: sarcoma (rare).</ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                        </ce:list>
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0120">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0125">Calf, thigh or buttock pain on exertion (claudication)
                    </ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0420">Intermittent claudication due to peripheral vascular disease causes calf, thigh
                        or buttock pain on exercise. The amount of exercise required to cause pain tends to be
                        consistent although it often deteriorates slowly. It is relieved within a predictable period of
                        time on rest.
                    </ce:para>
                    <ce:para id="p0425">Spinal claudication due to spinal stenosis also causes calf, thigh or buttock
                        pain on exertion, possibly by causing occlusion of the spinal arteries. However, the
                        claudication distance tends to be variable.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
            </ce:section>
            <ce:section id="s0125">
                <ce:section-title id="st0130">Respiratory symptoms</ce:section-title>
                <ce:section id="s0130">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0135">Dyspnoea</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0430">Clarify the degree of dyspnoea and its consequences for everyday tasks; try and
                        separate respiratory dyspnoea from cardiac causes though there is much overlap (see<ce:intra-ref
                                xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00005-8" id="ia0045">Ch. 5</ce:intra-ref>).
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0135">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0140">Cough</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0435">The causes of cough are multiple. Associated features will help in developing a
                        sensible differential diagnosis (see<ce:intra-ref xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00007-1"
                                                                          id="ia0050">Ch. 7</ce:intra-ref>).
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0140">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0145">Sputum</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0440">How much sputum is produced? Ask about its colour, texture and time course:
                        <ce:list id="l0040">
                            <ce:list-item id="u0220">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0445">Yellow/green: usually infection, acute asthma (due to
                                    eosinophils).
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0225">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0450">Frothy: pulmonary oedema.</ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0230">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0455">Rusty: lobar pneumonia (pneumococcal).</ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0235">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0460">Blood: pulmonary embolism, lung cancer, pneumonia (see<ce:intra-ref
                                        xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00007-1" id="ia0055">Ch. 7</ce:intra-ref>).
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0240">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0465">Taste: foul in bronchiectasis and abscess.</ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0245">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0470">Smell: foul in bronchiectasis.</ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                        </ce:list>
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0145">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0150">Chest pain</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0475">Needs a careful assessment of character, position, timing, precipitating
                        factors, etc. Chest pain is usually pleuritic in respiratory disease (<ce:intra-ref
                                xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00004-6" id="ia0060">Ch. 4</ce:intra-ref>) and is
                        potentially due to pneumonia, pneumothorax or pulmonary embolus.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0150">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0155">Wheeze</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0480">Patients with airways obstruction sometimes notice an audible expiratory
                        wheeze.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0155">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0160">Hoarse voice</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0485">This may be caused, for example, by recurrent laryngeal nerve palsy in bronchial
                        carcinoma.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
            </ce:section>
            <ce:section id="s0160">
                <ce:section-title id="st0165">Gastrointestinal disease</ce:section-title>
                <ce:section id="s0165">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0170">Abdominal pain</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0490">Establish the site, radiation, character, exacerbating and relieving factors,
                        and severity. This is discussed in detail in<ce:intra-ref
                                xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00014-9" id="ia0065">Ch. 14</ce:intra-ref>.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0170">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0175">Dysphagia</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0495">Dysphagia means difficulty in swallowing. Ask about:
                        <ce:list id="l0045">
                            <ce:list-item id="u0250">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0500">The onset and progression of symptoms</ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0255">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0505">Where do things get stuck? This may give a clue as to the site of
                                    the lesion.
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0260">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0510">Is there difficulty with solids, fluids or both? Neuromuscular
                                    disorders tend to present with dysphagia for fluids at onset, whereas mechanical
                                    obstruction results in dysphagia for solids at onset.
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                        </ce:list>
                    </ce:para>
                    <ce:para id="p0515">The causes of dysphagia are outlined in
                        <ce:cross-ref refid="f0020">Fig. 1.3</ce:cross-ref>
                        <ce:float-anchor refid="f0020"/>.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0175">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0180">Nausea and vomiting</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0520">What does the vomitus look like?
                        <ce:list id="l0050">
                            <ce:list-item id="u0265">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0525">Yellow-green: upper gastrointestinal (GI) contents plus bile.
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0270">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0530">Brown (faeculant): lower small bowel contents.</ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0275">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0535">Bright-red blood: active upper GI bleeding (<ce:intra-ref
                                        xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00010-1" id="ia0070">Ch. 10</ce:intra-ref>).
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0280">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0540">‘Coffee grounds’: ‘old’ upper GI bleeding.</ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                        </ce:list>
                    </ce:para>
                    <ce:para id="p0545">How ‘violent’ was the vomiting? Projectile vomiting indicates pyloric stenosis,
                        most commonly seen in infants, but may arise as a consequence of duodenal ulceration in adults.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0180">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0185">Indigestion</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0550">‘Heartburn’ or ‘dyspepsia’ is due to reflux of the gastric contents into the
                        oesophagus. Be aware that heartburn can easily be confused with cardiac chest pain. Always
                        explore these symptoms carefully.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0185">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0190">Change in bowel habit or stools</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0555">Has there been a change? Ask about diarrhoea and constipation, or the presence
                        of one alternating with the other (see<ce:intra-ref xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00011-3"
                                                                            id="ia0075">Ch. 11</ce:intra-ref>).
                    </ce:para>
                    <ce:para id="p0560">Is there any rectal bleeding? Is the bleeding with or without mucus? The causes
                        of rectal bleeding are summarized in
                        <ce:cross-ref refid="f0025">Fig. 1.4</ce:cross-ref>
                        <ce:float-anchor refid="f0025"/>. Anal and rectal lesions result in fresh blood on the outside
                        of the stool, on the paper on wiping, or in the pan. Higher lesions result in blood intermixed
                        with the stool. Melaena implies upper GI bleeding and the passage of altered blood originating
                        proximal to the hepatic flexure.
                    </ce:para>
                    <ce:para id="p0565">Inquire about tenesmus. Tenesmus is the painful desire to defecate when there is
                        no stool in the rectum. This is due to a lesion in the lumen or wall of the rectum mimicking
                        faeces.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
            </ce:section>
            <ce:section id="s0190">
                <ce:section-title id="st0195">Jaundice and itch</ce:section-title>
                <ce:para id="p0570">Jaundice can be insidious or acute and the patient may therefore not have noticed
                    it. Ask family or friends whether they have noticed a change in skin colour. Itching is caused by
                    build-up of bile salts in the skin and is a feature of obstructice jaundice (see<ce:intra-ref
                            xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00013-7" id="ia0080">Ch. 13</ce:intra-ref>). It can be
                    asked about directly and may even be evident on clinical examination through scratch marks. Jaundice
                    may indicate liver impairment and bruising and should therefore be asked about directly as clotting
                    factor biosynthesis may be impaired.
                </ce:para>
            </ce:section>
            <ce:section id="s0195">
                <ce:section-title id="st0200">Abdominal swelling</ce:section-title>
                <ce:para id="p0575">Ask whether the patient has noticed a change to the size of their abdomen (be
                    careful not to offend patients by assuming they have an acutely distended abdomen!). Remember the 7
                    <ce:hsp sp="0.25"/>F's: Foetus, Flatus, Fat, Fluid, Flipping great mass, Faeces and Full bladder.
                </ce:para>
            </ce:section>
            <ce:section id="s0200">
                <ce:section-title id="st0205">Genitourinary symptoms</ce:section-title>
                <ce:section id="s0205">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0210">Dysuria</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0580">This is discomfort during or after micturition due to urinary tract infection or
                        recent urethral instrumentation (catheter or cystoscope).
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0210">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0215">Change in urine appearance</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0585">What does the urine look like?
                        <ce:list id="l0055">
                            <ce:list-item id="u0285">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0590">Cloudy: infection, precipitated urates or phosphates.</ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0290">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0595">Frothy: proteinuria.</ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0295">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0600">Orange: very concentrated urine, bilirubin, rifampicin.</ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0300">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0605">Red/smoky: haematuria, haemoglobinuria, myoglobinuria, rifampicin,
                                    ‘black water fever’ due to haemolysis in
                                    <ce:italic>Plasmodium falciparum</ce:italic>
                                    malaria, eating beetroot.
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0305">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0610">Dark on standing: porphyria.</ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0310">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0615">Green: drugs containing methylene blue (commercial analgesics).
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                        </ce:list>
                    </ce:para>
                    <ce:para id="p0620">See
                        <ce:intra-ref xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00016-2" id="ia0085">Ch. 16</ce:intra-ref>
                        for the causes of haematuria and proteinuria.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0215">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0220">Frequency and nocturia</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0625">Increased frequency of micturition can be due to:
                        <ce:list id="l0060">
                            <ce:list-item id="u0315">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0630">Bladder irritation: infection, stones, tumour.</ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0320">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0635">Outflow obstruction: prostatic hypertrophy, urethral stricture.
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0325">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0640">Neurological: multiple sclerosis, cauda equina syndrome.</ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                        </ce:list>
                    </ce:para>
                    <ce:para id="p0645">Note that, in polyuria, there is an increased volume of urine as well as
                        frequency of micturition.
                    </ce:para>
                    <ce:para id="p0650">Nocturia can be due to any of the causes of polyuria (see<ce:intra-ref
                            xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00015-0" id="ia0090">Ch. 15</ce:intra-ref>) and increased
                        frequency.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0220">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0225">Hesitancy</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0655">Hesitancy followed by a poor stream with terminal dribbling are features of
                        prostatic enlargement. These symptoms are often associated with benign prostatic hypertrophy,
                        but could indicate carcinoma of the prostate.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0225">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0230">Loin pain</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0660">This can be associated with renal disease (<ce:intra-ref
                            xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00012-5" id="ia0095">Ch. 14</ce:intra-ref>).
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0230">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0235">Incontinence</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0665">This can be either urge incontinence (e.g. detrusor instability) or stress
                        incontinence (e.g. weak pelvic musculature following childbirth). It can be functional, as
                        people with mobility problems may not be able to get to the loo quickly enough.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0235">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0240">Menstruation</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0670">Determine the pattern of the normal cycle. Then ask about flow (heavy or light),
                        intermenstrual bleeding, postcoital bleeding or dysmenorrhoea.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0240">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0245">Discharge</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0675">Vaginal or penile discharge can indicate infection.</ce:para>
                </ce:section>
            </ce:section>
            <ce:section id="s0245">
                <ce:section-title id="st0250">Neurological symptoms</ce:section-title>
                <ce:section id="s0250">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0255">Headache</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0680">This is a difficult symptom for the doctor, with the diagnosis ranging from the
                        trivial to the fatal. Ask about red flag symptoms (see<ce:intra-ref
                                xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00018-6" id="ia0100">Ch. 18</ce:intra-ref>).
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0255">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0260">Dizziness</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0685">This can also be unsteadiness (
                        <ce:intra-ref xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00022-8" id="ia0105">Chs 22</ce:intra-ref>
                        and<ce:intra-ref xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00026-5" id="ia0110">26</ce:intra-ref>).
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0260">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0265">Blackouts</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0690">See<ce:intra-ref xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00022-8" id="ia0115">Ch.
                        22</ce:intra-ref>.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0265">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0270">Visual disturbance</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0695">Vision can be affected by lesions of the optic pathway, of the nerves
                        controlling eye movements (third, fourth, sixth) or conjugate gaze.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0270">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0275">Altered hearing</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0700">Ask about deafness, tinnitus and vertigo (<ce:intra-ref
                            xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00027-7" id="ia0120">Ch. 27</ce:intra-ref>).
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0275">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0280">Altered smell</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0705">Anosmia can result from head injury, nasal polyps, following viral upper
                        respiratory tract infections or frontal lobe tumours.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0280">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0285">Speech disturbance</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0710">There are three types of disordered speech:
                        <ce:list id="l0065">
                            <ce:list-item id="u0330">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0715">Dysarthria: difficulty in articulating speech but language content
                                    is completely normal.
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0335">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0720">Dysphonia: difficulty in voice production.</ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                            <ce:list-item id="u0340">
                                <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                                <ce:para id="p0725">Dysphasia: difficulty in understanding or expressing language,
                                    caused by lesions affecting the dominant cerebral hemisphere (usually the left).
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:list-item>
                        </ce:list>
                    </ce:para>
                    <ce:para id="p0730">
                        <ce:cross-ref refid="f0030">Fig. 1.5</ce:cross-ref>
                        <ce:float-anchor refid="f0030"/>
                        shows the characteristic speech abnormalities that result from lesions at specific anatomical
                        sites.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
            </ce:section>
            <ce:section id="s0285">
                <ce:section-title id="st0290">Limb weakness, paraesthesiae and sensory loss</ce:section-title>
                <ce:para id="p0735">These are covered in detail in<ce:intra-ref
                        xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00034-4" id="ia0125">Ch. 34</ce:intra-ref>.
                </ce:para>
            </ce:section>
            <ce:section id="s0290">
                <ce:section-title id="st0295">Metabolic and endocrine symptoms</ce:section-title>
                <ce:para id="p0740">Symptoms associated with metabolic and endocrine problems are varied and multiple –
                    these symptoms are described in detail in<ce:intra-ref xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00035-6"
                                                                           id="ia0130">Ch. 35</ce:intra-ref>. The two
                    most common endocrine conditions to consider and ask about are disorders of the thyroid (
                    <ce:cross-ref refid="f0035">Fig. 1.6</ce:cross-ref>
                    <ce:float-anchor refid="f0035"/>) and diabetes (
                    <ce:cross-ref refid="f0040">Fig. 1.7</ce:cross-ref>
                    <ce:float-anchor refid="f0040"/>).
                </ce:para>
            </ce:section>
            <ce:section id="s0295">
                <ce:section-title id="st0300">Musculoskeletal symptoms</ce:section-title>
                <ce:section id="s0300">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0305">Weakness</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0745">This is covered in detail in<ce:intra-ref
                            xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00034-4" id="ia0135">Ch. 34</ce:intra-ref>.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0305">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0310">Pain</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0750">Pain can arise in the muscles (<ce:intra-ref
                            xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00024-1" id="ia0140">Ch. 24</ce:intra-ref>), joints (
                        <ce:intra-ref xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00019-8" id="ia0145">Ch. 19</ce:intra-ref>), or
                        bones (
                        <ce:cross-ref refid="f0045">Fig. 1.8</ce:cross-ref>
                        <ce:float-anchor refid="f0045"/>).
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0310">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0315">Stiffness</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0755">Stiffness, particularly after inactivity (e.g. early morning stiffness), is a
                        feature of inflammation.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0315">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0320">Joint swelling</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0760">This can be caused by infection, inflammation, blood (haemarthrosis) or crystal
                        deposition.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0320">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0325">Disability</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0765">How do the symptoms affect lifestyle? This is extremely important in patients
                        with rheumatological diseases.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
            </ce:section>
            <ce:section id="s0325">
                <ce:section-title id="st0330">Skin symptoms</ce:section-title>
                <ce:section id="s0330">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0335">Rash</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0770">The distribution may be very helpful in determining the diagnosis (<ce:intra-ref
                            xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00021-6" id="ia0150">Ch. 21</ce:intra-ref>).
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0335">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0340">Pruritus</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0775">For the causes of pruritus, see<ce:cross-ref refid="f0015">Fig.
                        1.2</ce:cross-ref>.
                    </ce:para>
                </ce:section>
                <ce:section id="s0340">
                    <ce:section-title id="st0345">Precipitants</ce:section-title>
                    <ce:para id="p0780">Has there been any recent change in detergents, soap, shampoo, etc.?</ce:para>
                </ce:section>
            </ce:section>
            <ce:section id="s0345">
                <ce:section-title id="st0350">Haematological symptoms</ce:section-title>
                <ce:para id="p0785">These can be summarized as follows:
                    <ce:list id="l0070">
                        <ce:list-item id="u0345">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0790">Symptoms of anaemia: low haemoglobin (<ce:intra-ref
                                    xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00029-0" id="ia0155">Ch. 29</ce:intra-ref>).
                            </ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                        <ce:list-item id="u0350">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0795">Recurrent infections: low white cell count.</ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                        <ce:list-item id="u0355">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0800">Bleeding or bruising: low platelets (<ce:intra-ref
                                    xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7234-3864-9.00028-9" id="ia0160">Ch. 28</ce:intra-ref>).
                            </ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                        <ce:list-item id="u0360">
                            <ce:label>•</ce:label>
                            <ce:para id="p0805">Any recent glandular swelling?</ce:para>
                        </ce:list-item>
                    </ce:list>
                </ce:para>
            </ce:section>
        </ce:section>
        <ce:section id="s0350">
            <ce:section-title id="st0355">CONCLUSION OF HISTORY TAKING</ce:section-title>
            <ce:para id="p0810">The way to become skilled in history taking for both clinical practice and examinations
                is to try and clerk as many patients as you can with the range of listed presentations. It is important
                to write these up with a list of diagnoses and a plan, then practise presenting to other people. Then
                ask yourself how you could do it better next time.
                <ce:display>
                    <ce:textbox role="alt0" id="b0020">
                        <ce:textbox-head>
                            <ce:title>HINTS AND TIPS</ce:title>
                        </ce:textbox-head>
                        <ce:textbox-body>
                            <ce:sections>
                                <ce:para id="p0815">At the end of the history ask two questions:</ce:para>
                                <ce:para id="p0820">‘Is there anything else you are worried about or want to tell me?’
                                    It is possible that the patient may now feel ready to tell you about their main
                                    concern.
                                </ce:para>
                                <ce:para id="p0825">‘Is there anything that you are worried this might be?’ There is
                                    often visible relief when this question is asked and it enables you to address the
                                    patient's real feelings about their illness.
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:sections>
                        </ce:textbox-body>
                    </ce:textbox>
                </ce:display>
                <ce:display>
                    <ce:textbox role="alt0" id="b0025">
                        <ce:textbox-head>
                            <ce:title>HINTS AND TIPS</ce:title>
                        </ce:textbox-head>
                        <ce:textbox-body>
                            <ce:sections>
                                <ce:para id="p0830">Good history taking is not easily taught or learnt the night before
                                    an examination. It is acquired through experience, lots of it!
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:sections>
                        </ce:textbox-body>
                    </ce:textbox>
                </ce:display>
                <ce:display>
                    <ce:textbox role="alt0" id="b0030">
                        <ce:textbox-head>
                            <ce:title>HINTS AND TIPS</ce:title>
                        </ce:textbox-head>
                        <ce:textbox-body>
                            <ce:sections>
                                <ce:para id="p0835">Be careful not to label a patient's symptoms as ‘functional’. All
                                    organic causes must be ruled out before making this diagnosis – it is a diagnosis of
                                    exclusion.
                                </ce:para>
                            </ce:sections>
                        </ce:textbox-body>
                    </ce:textbox>
                </ce:display>
            </ce:para>
        </ce:section>
    </ce:sections>
</chapter>